（1984年11月）
（戈尔巴乔夫上台前  一艘台风级苏联潜艇）
（在大浅滩南部浮出水面）
（但似乎是遭遇了辐射问题  随即下潜）
（一份未经证实的报告称部分船员获救生还）
（但根据苏联及美国政府所提出的声明）
（这一切完全都是）
（无稽之谈）
（靠近摩尔曼斯克）
（玻利尼亚湾）
今天早晨真冷，船长
Cold this morning, Captain.
是啊
Cold.
冷的刺骨
And hard.
是时候了，舰长
It's time, captain.
到时候了
It's time.
该行动了
Time indeed.
《猎杀红色十月》
（舰队战术  詹尼斯号战舰）
（美国大词典  海军战舰）
（内战海军简史）
（会议记录）
你在干什么？你现在应该在楼上睡觉
What are you doing? You're supposed to be upstairs sleeping.
斯坦利一直吵醒我
Stanley keeps waking me up.
原来是这样
I get it.
你越来越重了
Boy, are you getting heavy.
别老让她牵着鼻子走
Don't let her pull more than her usual nonsense.
已讲过两个故事和喝两杯水了
Two stories, two glasses of water.
杰克，你要错过航班了
Jack, you're going to miss the plane.
好吧，小蟋蟀，听我说
Okay. Cricket, you listen to me.
现在跟维勒夫人上楼去睡觉
Go upstairs with Mrs. Wheeler now and go to sleep.
我出差回来的时候，会给斯坦利带来一个弟弟
On my business trip, I'll get Stanley a little brother.
你保证？
Will you promise?
我保证
I promise.
（伦敦希思罗机场  国际航班出港）
先生，需要些什么吗？
Can I get you anything, sir?
不用了，谢谢
No, thank you very much.
如果你试着睡一下的话，时间会过得快些
If you try and get sleep, the flight will go faster.
我在飞机上睡不着
I can never sleep on a plane.
因为乱流
Turbulence.
什么？
Pardon?
乱流，太阳辐射加热了地表
Turbulence. Solar radiation heats the earth's crust,
热空气上升，冷空气下降
warm air rises, cold air descends.
我不喜欢乱流
Turbulence. I don't like that.
还是试着睡一下吧
Try to sleep anyway.
（欢迎来到美国）
莱恩博士吗？
Dr. Ryan?
（中央情报局）
杰克，快进来
Jack, boy, get yourself in here.
老天！你看起来气色真差
Jesus! You look like hell.
感谢你的恭维，长官
Thank you very much, Admiral.
- 要喝咖啡吗？  - 我正需要一杯
- Want coffee? - I think I need some coffee.
我不想问你旅途的情况
I'm not going to ask you how your flight went.
你上次睡觉是什么时候？
When's the last time you got some sleep?
我不知道，我的表还没调过来
I don't know. This thing's still on London time.
- 要加奶精或糖吗？  - 都要加
- Milk and sugar? - Milk and sugar.
卡洛琳还好吗？
So how's Caroline?
我们上次见面
Last time I saw her
是在你缅因州爷爷家吧？
was at your granddad's place in Maine, wasn't it?
她很好，她要我问候你
She's fine. Sends you her best.
莎莉呢？
And Sally?
她很好
She's fine.
她现在几岁了，三岁？
What is she now, three?
不，她是个早熟的五岁小孩
No, she's a very precocious five.
她前几天才对我们说
She announced to Caroline and I the other day
如果我们买个弟弟给她
that her life would be considerably less lonely
她就不会这么孤独
if we were to buy her a baby brother.
但是…
But...
后来她决定只要帮斯坦利买个弟弟就够了
she decided it would be enough if we were to buy one for Stanley.
谁是斯坦利？
Who's Stanley?
斯坦利是一只玩具熊
Stanley's a bear.
好吧，到底是什么大事？
All right. What's important enough to get you on a plane
让你在连夜赶来这？
in the middle of the night?
两天前英国情报局拿到这些照片
British Intelligence obtained these pictures two days ago.
她是红色十月
She's the Red October,
最新型的台风级潜艇
the latest Typhoon class.
真是个大家伙
Big son of a bitch.
比一般的台风级潜艇
Twelve meters longer than the standard Typhoon.
长度多12米，宽多3米
Three meters wider.
舰长叫雷米思
The captain's name is Ramius.
- 你认识他？  - 对，我去年为他写过自传
- One of yours? - Yeah. I did his bio last year.
过去十年他一直是苏联新潜艇的试航指挥官
He's taken out the lead boat in each new sub class for 10 years.
政界关系良好
Fairly good political connections.
大部分的舰长都是他训练的
Trained most of their attack boat skippers.
俄国人称他为维尔纽斯总教头
The Russians call him Vilnius nastavnik.
维尔纽斯司令
The Vilnius schoolmaster.
这些门做什么用的？
What are these doors?
那些门
Those doors, sir,
正是问题所在
are the problem.
我不知道它们是什么，英国人也不清楚
I don't know what they are. Neither do the British.
也许我们在摩尔曼斯克的朋友又发明些新东西了
Perhaps our friends in Murmansk have come up with something new.
我想把这些照片拿给别人看看
With your permission, I'd like to show these to someone.
- 听过史基・泰勒吗？  - 潜艇驾驶员
- Do you know Skip Tyler? - Sub driver.
曾经是，被人酒醉驾车撞断了腿
Was. Clipped by a drunk driver. Lost his leg.
现在在军校教书，也是海军研究室的顾问
He's teaching at the academy, consulting for navy labs.
- 他的权限？  - 能检阅最高机密文件
- Clearance? - Top secret or better.
玛姬，帮莱恩博士十分钟内在楼下备好一辆车
Margie, have a car for Dr. Ryan downstairs in 10 minutes.
今早有卫星在玻利尼亚湾侦测到红色十月的踪影
A satellite caught Red October in Polijarny Inlet this morning.
（达拉斯号美国军舰  洛杉矶级攻击潜艇）
（玻利尼亚湾西北100哩处）
你听到了吗？
Do you hear it?
没有
No.
博蒙特，以前我们在学校时一边睡都能做这档事
Beaumont, at Cal Tech we used to do this in our sleep.
现在听到了吗？
You hear it now?
等一下，或许…
Wait a minute. Maybe.
- 被海面的波浪声盖住了？  - 对
- It's buried in surface clutter? - Yes.
- 现在应该用分析仪？  - 没错
- I should go to SAPS? - Correct,
希曼・博蒙特
Seaman Beaumont.
利用声纳分析处理系统
Signal algorithmic processing systems.
再学一个星期，你就能回加州理工教书了
Give it a week, and you'll be teaching at Cal Tech.
所以…
So...
就像贝多芬在电脑上谱曲Like Beethoven on the computer,
透过分析仪分析结果
you have labored to produce
一种生物
a biologic.
什么？
A what?
鲸鱼，博蒙特，一头鲸鱼
A whale, Beaumont. A whale.
一种更懂声纳系统的海洋哺乳动物
A marine mammal that knows a hell of a lot more about sonar
比你懂
than you do.
关掉分析仪
Kill the SAPS.
对准269航道
Train over to 2-6-9 and...
我们再试一次
let's try it again.
小子，他如果再刁难你
If he gets to ragging on you too bad,
就问他关于帕瓦罗蒂的事情
ask him about Pavarotti.
我们没时间讲故事
We don't have time for sea stories.
我正在教博蒙特水兵
I was in the middle of teaching Seaman Beaumont
认识现代声纳系统，现在…
the intricacies of modern sonar. Now...
我不是指挥官，我是森林女王席娜
I ain't chief of the boat. I'm Sheena, Queen of the Jungle.
- 拜托你，参谋长  - 得了吧，告诉我
- Cob, please. - Come on, Cob. Tell me.
好吧
Okay.
好
Fine.
请继续
Go ahead.
这位琼斯水兵
Seaman Jones here,
非常喜爱音乐
he's into music in a big way.
他认为整艘潜艇
He figures this whole boat is basically
就是他个人私人录音室
just his own personal, private stereo set.
- 他正在听帕瓦罗蒂的这首…  - 是帕格尼尼
- He gets this piece of Pavarotti... - He was Paganini.
- 管他的  - 是帕格尼尼
- Whatever. - Paganini.
是我在说故事，好吗？
This is my story, okay?
那要说对
Tell it right.
帕瓦罗蒂是男高音，帕格尼尼是作曲家
Pavarotti's a tenor. Paganini was a composer.
反正他把这音乐对外播放
Okay. So he's got this music, and he's got it out in the water.
然后戴上自己耳机收听，陶醉得不得了
He's listening on his headsets, happy as a clam.
然后就天下大乱了
Then all hell breaks loose.
- 在圣地亚哥外海的船舰…  - 还有一艘在珍珠港的船舰
- A slew of boats out of San Diego... - Including one way out at Pearl.
还有一艘在珍珠港的船舰
Including one way out at Pearl.
突然间，他们都听见帕瓦罗蒂的歌声
All of a sudden, they start hearing Pavarotti.
- 帕瓦罗蒂…  - 就这样被播放出来
- Pavarotti... - Coming out of their asses.
- 我该怎么办？  - 收到了
- What do I do? - I got it.
主控室，097方未发现不明物
Conn, Sonar. New contact, bearing 0-9-7.
指定代号为山脊35
Designate contact number Sierra 3-5.
我是舰长，侦测到什么，琼斯？
Captain, aye. What've you got, Jones?
一个很远的信号，可能是潜艇
Distant contact, probably submerged.
只是胡乱猜测
It's a wild guess,
不过我有不好的预感
but I'd say we hit a boomer coming out of the barn.
可能是从玻利尼亚湾来的飞弹潜艇
Could be a missile boat out of Polijarny.
好吧，继续追踪，我马上就来
Okay. Start your track. I'll be there in a minute.
是的，长官
Sonar, aye.
该打开指令了，舰长
Time to open the orders, sir.
政委正在您的舱房等你
The Political Officer is in your cabin.
很好
Very well.
你来指挥
You have the conn.
你在做什么？
What are you doing?
我在监管船员的稳定性，舰长
I must oversee the stability of the crew, Captain.
你侵犯了我的隐私权
By invading my privacy?
苏联并没有个人隐私，同志
Privacy is not a major concern in the Soviet Union, comrade.
它会破坏集体利益
It's often contrary to the collective good.
“你看，我生来就是窃贼…”
"Behold, I am coming as a thief...
“人们全被带到”
"And they gathered them together
“一个叫做…”
"In a place called...
“世界末日的战场”
"Armageddon."
“天使将她酒杯洒向空中”
"And the seventh angel poured forth his bowl into the air,
一个来自天堂的声音说
"and a voice cried out from heaven, saying,
“都结束了”
"'It is done."'
堂堂指挥官竟然对世界末日有兴趣
A man with your responsibilities reading about the end of the world.
这又是什么？
And what's this?
“我代表死神”
"I am become death,
“毁掉了全世界”
the destroyer of worlds."
这是一个美国人引述古印度圣经的话
It is an ancient Hindu text quoted by an American.
美国人？
American?
他发明了原子弹
He invented the atomic bomb,
后来被指控为共产党员
and he was later accused of being a communist.
你还在这些话下面划线加注解
You wrote and underlined these passages?
不是
No.
这本书是我妻子的
This book belonged to my wife.
我把书留下来纪念她
I keep it for sentimental value.
我很遗憾，舰长同志，你的妻子很美丽
I'm sorry, Comrade Captain. Your wife was a beautiful woman.
我为她的死感到遗憾
Her death was unfortunate.
我只是在履行我的职责，这是我的责任
I'm only doing my job. It is my responsibility.
苏联国家安全委员会在我的潜艇安插多少特务？
How many agents did the KGB put aboard my boat?
- 你的潜艇，舰长？  - 没错
- Your boat, Captain? - Yes.
这艘舰艇是属于苏联人民的
This vessel belongs to the people of the Soviet Union.
另外
Besides,
即使他们真的派特务到船上
if the KGB or the GRU has agents aboard,
我也不会知道
I will be the last to know.
打开指令吧，舰长
I suggest we open our orders, Captain.
当然，同志
Certainly, comrade.
来自指挥部…
"From Commander...
战略潜艇红旗北方舰队
"Strategic submarine forces red banner northern fleet."
继续向北航行到座标5490的地方
We're to proceed north to grid square reference 54-90
与科诺瓦罗夫号潜艇会合
and rendezvous with Alfa submarine Konovalov.
图波列夫舰长的潜艇
Captain Tupolev's boat.
你认识他？
You know Tupolev?
我知道他是贵族之后
I know he descends from aristocracy...
他曾是你的学生
and that he was your student.
据说你在他心中占有很重要的位置
It's rumored he has a special place in his heart for you.
图波列夫的心中只有他自己
There's little room in Tupolev's heart for anyone but Tupolev.
跟他会合后
Having made contact,
我们会进行一系列的军演
we are to run a series of drills.
图波列夫会趁我们测试潜艇时追击我们
Tupolev will hunt us while we test our ship.
测试过本舰的履带推进系统后
Having evaluated the operational readiness of the caterpillar drive,
我们会在本月16日返抵玻利尼亚湾
we are to return to Polijarny on or about the 16th of this month.
船长
Captain,
现在对我们来说是历史性的时刻
this is an historic moment.
我有一个请求
I'd like to make a request.
- 在你开始之前，同志…  - 我知道这不合规矩
- Before you proceed, comrade... - I know it's not protocol,
但是否能将我们任务
but would you permit me to post our orders
告知全体船员
and inform the crew of our mission?
我现在要去的地方不是你能来的
Where I'm going, you cannot follow.
帕契夫医官
Dr. Petrov,
马上到舰长室报到
report to my cabin immediately.
这里发生了可怕的意外
There's been a dreadful accident.
（船坞4号  美国海军造船厂）
（帕都森，马里兰州）
伙计
Buddy!
丹尼，我需要更多的焊棒
Daniel, got any more rods? More rods!
听我说，这下面没有托架
Listen to me. There's no cradle underneath it.
把它反过来
Get it over.
轻松点，别哩嗦的
Relax! Stop being an old maid.
不然你自己来做
You want to come up here and do it yourself?
- 好吧，把她弄上来  - 什么？
- All right. Bring her up. - What? What?
莱恩！
Ryan!
谁让你进来的？
Who let you in here?
别提那个了
Skip,
你现在改玩这些模型？
what, have they got you playing with models now?
妈的，比尔！叫他们慢一点！
Damn it, Bill! Tell them to slow down!
我在做了，你们能慢点吗？
I'm doing it. I'm doing it. Slow it down, will you?
这不是模型
It's not a model.
这是DSRV
The DSRV.
救援潜艇
escue sub.
我知道，只是以前从来没见过，你准备怎么做？
I know what it is. What are you doing with it?
我们打算改装它
We're rigging it with a generic docking collar
以便配合英、德及其他潜艇
so it'll mate with British, German... Just about anybody's sub.
这玩意能够在24小时内到达世界各地
We can get it anywhere in the world in 24 hours.
- 你的背好了吗？  - 还好
- How's your back? - It's fine.
你有空吗？
Have you got a minute?
比一般潜艇大
Bigger than a regular Typhoon.
这些门是做什么的？
What are these doors?
你也注意到了
You don't miss much, do you?
看起来比鱼雷管大
Those are too big to be torpedo tubes.
能用来发射洲际弹道飞弹吗？
Would you launch an ICBM horizontally?
当然，但为何要那样做？它们是对称的
Sure. Why would you want to? They're symmetrical.
就在艇轴线正下方
Right down the long axis of the sub.
会不会是声纳探测器？
How about a towed sonar array?
不可能，离螺旋桨太近了
Nope. Too close to the screws.
我将要…
I'll be...
这可能是履带装置
This... This could be a caterpillar.
- 什么？  - 一种履带推进器
- A what? - A caterpillar drive.
磁流体推进系统
Magneto-hydrodynamic propulsion.
- 听得懂吗？  - 不懂
- You follow? - No.
就像水中喷射引擎
It's like a jet engine for the water.
海水从潜艇的前方进入，从后方喷出
Goes in the front, gets squirted out the back.
由于没有零件，所以非常地安静
Only it's got no moving parts, so it's very, very quiet.
能有多安静？
Like how quiet?
安静到我们声纳系统无法探测到
It's doubtful our sonar would even pick it up.
就算侦测到
And if it did,
也会以为是鲸鱼或其他生物的声音
it would sound like whales humping or a seismic anomaly.
不会知道那是潜艇
Anything but a submarine.
我们几年前也研究过
We messed with this a couple of years ago.
但都没有成功
Couldn't make it work.
这真的是潜艇吗？会不会只是模型？
They really built this? This isn't a mock-up or anything?
它今早出海了
She put to sea this morning.
12岁时
When I was 12,
我曾帮我父亲把地下室改造成防空洞
I helped my daddy build a bomb shelter in our basement
只因有人将十几枚炸弹
because some fool parked a dozen warheads
瞄准佛罗里达州沿岸
90 miles off the coast of Florida.
这家伙能对华盛顿及纽约
This thing could park a couple of hundred warheads
发射上百枚飞弹
off Washington and New York,
而且是神不知鬼不觉
and no one would know anything about it until it was all over.
你没事吧，舰长？
Are you all right, Captain?
没事
Yes.
只是有点震惊他竟然被茶水绊倒而猝死
It's just to die for something as petty as slipping on tea.
舰长，不要责怪自己，那只是个意外
You're blaming yourself, Captain. It was an accident.
- 我们到那时你会感觉好些的  - 到哪？
- You'll feel better when we put in. - Put in?
回到基地，舰长
To base, Captain.
我们不能没有政委
We cannot go on without a political officer.
医官，这是一艘苏联战舰
Doctor, this is a combat vessel of the Soviet Navy,
而我是最高指战军官
and I'm a senior combat officer.
我们不能因为意外就取消行动
We do not cancel operations because of accidents.
水兵，到这来
Seaman, come here.
过来
Come here.
你的名字？
Your name?
我是二厨罗金诺夫，长官
Cook's Assistant Loginov, sir.
很好
Good.
我要你和医官共同见证
I want you and the doctor to witness this.
我拿下了政委的密钥…
I'm removing the political officer's missile key...
抬走吧
Carry on.
交由我自己保管
And I'm keeping it myself.
舰长，我们应该将此事呈报红色舰队指挥部
Captain, I think we should report this to Red Fleet Command.
不行，医官
I'm afraid that's impossible, Doctor.
上级指示不得使用无线电
Our orders are for strict radio silence.
指令，长官
Orders, sir.
- 你可以离开了，罗金诺夫  - 是，长官
- That's all, Loginov. - Yes, sir.
舰长，这样做并不合规定
This is most unnerving, Captain.
之所以会有两把密钥
The reason for having two missile keys
是以防任何人可以随意…
is so that no one man may...
随意什么？
May what?
随意发射飞弹，或许钥匙应该由我来保管
May arm the missiles. Perhaps I should keep the key.
- 谢谢你，医官  - 舰长
- Thank you. That'll be all, Doctor. - Captain, I...
等我向全体船员讲话时
When I address the crew,
你就会明白了
then you will understand.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
- 帕契夫  - 什么事，长官？
- Petrov. - Yes, sir?
我回报上级时不会提及有关你的评论
I will try to forget your comments when I present my report.
谢谢你，长官
Thank you, sir.
目前停在310航道
Holding steady on 3-1-0.
航速12节，大约2万码外
Twelve knots at about 20,000 yards.
有它的资料吗？
Have you got a make on him?
电脑正在分析，长官
Computer's chewing on it, sir.
双螺旋桨
Twin screws.
听起来像台风级潜艇
The plant noise sounds like a Typhoon.
（苏联台风级潜艇  没有任何过往记录）
长官，好像是新型潜艇
I'd say we got a new boat, sir.
汤米，之前有收到它的资料吗？
Tommy, I miss something on the boards?
目前没有任何纪录
Sub plant hasn't said anything about it.
好吧
All right.
电脑里有几艘台风级潜艇？
How many Typhoons we got in the computer?
六艘，长官
Six, sir.
好
Okay.
将它命名为台风七号
Call this guy Typhoon 7.
开始追踪录音，看是否能查到详细资料
Start a tape on him. See if we can work in a little closer.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
他们不会发觉吗？
Won't he hear us?
顺着它的航道就不会，博蒙特水兵
Not if we stay in his baffles, Seaman Beaumont.
跟在它的螺旋桨后
Not if we stay in his baffles.
从后方进入，他就不会听到任何声音
Come in behind his propeller, and he's deaf as a post.
卡马洛夫，声纳有发现异样吗？
Any sonar contacts, Mr. Kamarov?
没有异样，舰长
No contacts, Captain. The sonar is clear.
好，水面上有什么动静吗？伯罗丁先生
Good. Do we have any surface contacts, Mr. Borodin?
- 没有任何发现，长官  - 很好
- No contacts, sir. Scope is clear. - Good.
现在是向全体船员宣布上级命令的时候了
Then it is time I explain our orders to the crew.
同志们，我是你们的舰长
Comrades, this is your captain.
很荣幸能够和你们讲话
It is an honor to speak to you today,
也很荣幸能够和你们一起经历
and I'm honored to be sailing with you on the maiden voyage
我们祖国研究的最新式潜艇的处女航
of our motherland's most recent achievement.
我们又再一次，进入了这个生死攸关的危险游戏
And once more, we play our dangerous game,
对手就是
a game of chess,
我的的宿敌，美国海军
against our old adversary, the American Navy.
40年来
For 40 years,
你们的父兄
your fathers before you and your older brothers
已经和它们交战过数十回
played this game and played it well.
然而如今情势已不同
But today, the game is different.
我方略占上风
We have the advantage.
这让我想起过去那个辉煌的时期
It reminds me of the heady days of Sputnik and Yuri Gagarin,
过去人们曾因我们的火箭巨响而震惊
when the world trembled at the sound of our rockets.
今日它们将再度因我们的无声而诧异
They will tremble again at the sound of our silence.
启动无声推进系统
The order is engage for silent drive.
是，长官
Aye, sir.
控制室，打开外舱门
Ballast control, open outer doors.
收到，打开外舱门
Yes, open outer doors.
潜水命令
Diving command.
接合履带推进器，关闭主引擎
Engage caterpillar and secure main engines.
外舱门已打开，舰长
Doors opening, Captain.
同志们
Comrades,
我们的舰队仍不了解我们潜艇的性能
our own fleet doesn't know our full potential.
他们会尽全力追捕我们
They will do everything possible to test us,
但那只会让他们自惭形秽
but they will only test their own embarrassment.
我们将躲过追捕
We will leave our fleet behind.
穿越美军舰队的巡查
We will pass through the American patrols,
越过他们的声纳系统
pass their sonar nets,
当我们进行飞弹进攻时
and lay off their largest city...
将一边听他们的摇滚乐
and listen to their rock 'n' roll
边摧毁它们最大的城市
while we conduct missile drills.
然后…
Then...
在这些结束之后
And when we are finished,
他们唯一能听到的就是我们的欢呼声
the only sound they will hear is our laughter
当我们抵达哈瓦那时
while we sail to Havana,
迎接我们的将是同志般温暖的阳光
where the sun is warm and so is the comradeship.
降温装置准备已就绪，舰长
Cryogenic plant coming on line, Captain.
今天是伟大的一天，同志们
A great day, comrades.
我们正在改写历史
We sail into history.
履带接合就绪
Caterpillar engaging.
履带接合已就绪，舰长
Caterpillar engaging, Captain.
- 什么情况？  - 我不知道
- What happened? - I don't know.
- 左满舵  - 左满舵
- Full rudder left. - Full rudder left.
引航员，新航线250
Navigator. New course, 2-5-0.
- 新航线250  - 转向250
- Yes, new course, 2-5-0. - Steering 2-5-0.
新航线250
Yes, course is 2-5-0.
有声纳信号，舰长
Sonar contact, Captain.
在左后方，离我们很近
Port quarter. Close aboard.
是美国洛杉矶级潜艇
American, Los Angeles class.
- 是美国人，舰长…  - 在航线310
- American. Captain, we... - Course 3-1-0.
美军有没有跟来？
Is the American turning to follow us?
没有，舰长
No, Captain.
美军仍按原定航线行驶
The American is continuing in his original course.
继续向西北方向行进
He's continuing northwest.
他们听不到我们
He can't hear us.
那这些歌声呢？
And the singing?
让他们唱吧
Let them sing.
你说什么？检查你的传动装置
What are you talking about? Check your gear.
诊断器正在运作，舰长
Running diagnostics now, Captain.
声纳一切正常，俄国人都消失了
Sonar is working, Captain. The Russian disappeared.
一分钟前，他还在4000码外
One minute, he was steady 4,000 yards off the bow,
现在居然凭空消失
and then he was gone,
我刚刚好像听到了…
and for a second, I thought I heard...
听到什么？
Heard what?
听到了歌声，长官
I thought I heard singing, sir.
- 歌声？  - 是的，长官
- Singing? - Yes, sir.
（红色舰队政治指挥中心  莫斯科）
早安，长官
Good morning, sir.
希望你昨晚玩得很开心
I hope we had a lovely evening.
今天早晨有点冷
A little chilly this morning.
这有一封马可・雷米思寄来的信
There's a letter there from Marko Ramius.
马可
Marko.
喂
Yes?
不，我是莱恩博士
No. This is Dr. Ryan.
怎么回事？
What the hell happened?
跟我来
Come on.
这已不再是一个搜索任务了
This is no longer a research project.
我在门上发现了一条线
I got a line on those doors.
你知道那是什么吗？
You know what they are?
无声推进系统？
A nearly silent propulsion system?
你怎么知道的？
How did you know that?
我方潜艇追踪到它的信号
The captain of the sub following her radioed in.
之后却凭空消失
Thing disappeared right in front of him,
还不只这样
and that's only the half of it.
看看这个吧
Read.
对不起
I'm sorry.
有带证件吗？
Got your I.D.?
天啊！真令人无法相信
My God, this is unbelievable.
基洛夫号
The Kirov,
三艘斯德洛夫、基辅
three Sverdlovsk, the Kiev,
明斯克
the Minsk.
他们出动了所有的舰队
They've sortied their whole bloody fleet.
看来是这样
That's about the size of it.
（潜艇四级，白宫安全局）
- 下午好，司令  - 下午好，马修
- Good afternoon, Admiral. - Afternoon, Matthew.
我们要去哪？
Where are we going, anyway?
向杰弗瑞・派特做简报
Briefing for Jeffrey Pelt,
白宫安全局顾问
President's National Security Adviser.
大多数参谋总长都会列席
Most of the Joint Chiefs will be there,
及其他相关人士
along with a few other people.
谁要来做简报？
Who's giving the briefing?
你
You are.
文书官会帮你放映幻灯片
The yeoman will have all the slides laid out for you.
你只要上台就好
So all you got to do...
听着
Look,
没有人能比你更了解这份资料
no one understands this material better than you.
把你所知道有关潜艇的一切都告诉他
Just give him a rundown on the sub and a précis of the stuff in your hand.
他可能会问你一些问题
He's liable to ask some direct questions.
你就直言不讳，不必顾忌
Give him direct answers. Tell him what you think.
来吧
Come on.
各位，在过去的24小时我们看到
Gentlemen, the last 24 hours have seen
苏联海军有一些不寻常的举动
some extraordinary Soviet Naval activity.
首先是这艘船
The first to sail was this ship,
叫做“红色十月号”
we believe called the Red October
其名取自1917年的十月革命
in reference to the October Revolution of 1917.
是新型台风级潜艇
A variant of the Typhoon class,
船身长650英尺
she's some 650 feet long
有三万两千吨的排水量
and 32,000 tons submerged displacement,
大小可媲美二战时的航空母舰
roughly the same size as a World War II aircraft carrier.
我们认为船头和船尾的门内
We believe that these doors, here on the bow and again on the stern,
隐藏着一个特殊的传动系统
enclose a unique propulsion system,
磁力水流推进系统，或是履带式
a magneto-hydrodynamic drive, or caterpillar,
它能够使潜艇几乎无声的行进
that would enable the sub to run virtually silent.
这种新型传动系统
It is possible that this new drive system
让舰长，他叫雷米思
allowed the captain, a man named Ramius,
苏联最资深的潜艇指挥官
their senior and perhaps most respected commander...
有他的照片吗？
Do we have his picture available?
让雷米思逃过我们的达拉斯号的追踪
Allowed Ramius to elude one of our attack boats, the Dallas,
它今天早晨从港口开始追踪红色十月
which trailed Red October from harbor this morning.
而一旦启用了这套推进系统
It is also possible that this drive system, if operable,
红色十月号
could render the Red October
我们在大西洋的声纳监视系统根本无法监测到它
undetectable to our SOSUS warning nets in the Atlantic.
莱恩先生，你认为它是第一线攻击武器吗？
Mr. Ryan, would you characterize this as a first-strike weapon?
有可能，长官
That is a possibility, sir.
此舰的设计
It is designed to approach by stealth
就是针对目标
and to shower its target with multiple independent warheads
毫无预警的发射飞弹
with little or no warning before impact.
这东西根本就是为开战而设计的
Goddamn thing's made to start a war.
继续，莱恩先生
Proceed, Mr. Ryan.
达拉斯号跟丢了之后
About the same time the Dallas lost contact,
陆续有潜艇出港，从玻利尼亚湾…
there were additional sailings from Polijarny...
从波罗的海的列宁格勒，以及从地中海
and from Leningrad on the Baltic and from the Mediterranean.
目前约有58艘潜艇
There are now some 58 nuclear submarines
朝着大西洋全速前进
headed at high speed into the Atlantic.
今天下午在玻利尼亚湾上空的卫星侦测到
This afternoon a satellite pass over Polijarny found heat blooms
在明斯克有异常的舰队行动
in the engineering plants of the Kirov, the Minsk,
另外有20多艘巡洋舰及驱逐舰
and more than 20 other cruisers and destroyers,
目前正待命出港
indicating they were preparing to sail.
这是苏联有史以来最大的阵容
This constitutes the bulk of the Soviet surface fleet.
格里尔将军，你来作总结
Admiral Greer, your conclusions.
长官，这些数据并不能得出什么结论
Sir, the data support no conclusions as yet.
在太平洋没有侦测到活动
The absence of activity in the Pacific...
证明这可能只是一次…
suggests this could be just an...
演习
exercise.
- 这可能跟战事无关  - 假如不是演习呢？
- It may have nothing to do... - Suppose it's not an exercise?
假如这是和北约对抗的开端呢？
Suppose this is the beginning of a move against NATO?
这应该由国安局来回答，佩尔特先生
NSA can speak for that, Mr. Pelt.
我必须再次强调这事的高度机密性
I must emphasize the extreme sensitivity of this information
绝不能外泄
and that it not leave the room.
起航前
Before sailing,
雷米思舰长寄给尤里・帕多林将军一封信
Captain Ramius sent a letter to Admiral Yuri Padorin,
他是北方政治指挥中心红色舰队主席
Chairman of the Red Fleet Northern Political Directorate.
- 那是她的叔叔  - 谁的叔叔？
- That's her uncle. - Whose uncle?
雷米斯的妻子，帕多林是她的叔叔
Ramius' wife. Padorin's her uncle.
目前无从得知信的内容
Now, the contents of the letter are unknown,
但是帕多林将军立刻召见了
but Admiral Padorin immediately demanded
契尔年科总理
a meeting with Premier Chernenko,
会见持续了几分钟
and within minutes of that meeting,
之后苏联舰队即奉命出动追捕红色十月号
the Soviet fleet sailed with orders to find Red October...
并将之击沉
and sink her.
击沉它？
Sink her?
天啊，当中有多少核子潜舰
My God. They've got a madman on their hands.
如果它到达500哩外海内
If it gets within 500 miles of the coast,
我们只有两分钟的应变时间
we'll have less than two minutes' warning.
- 今天是23号吧？  - 什么？
- Today's the 23rd, isn't it? - What?
- 今天是不是23号？  - 是啊
- Is today the 23rd? - Yeah.
你这混蛋
You son of a bitch.
你这个混蛋
You son of a bitch!
你有什么要补充的吗，莱恩博士？
You wish to add something to our discussion, Dr. Ryan?
长官，我只是在想
Sir, I was just thinking
也许我们要考虑另外一种可能性
that perhaps there's another possibility we might consider.
雷米思可能是要叛变
Ramius might be trying to defect.
你在暗示这个人…
Do you mean to suggest that this man has come...
莱恩先生，请继续
Proceed, Mr. Ryan.
雷米思训练出大部分的军官干部
Ramius trained most of their officer corps,
这让他处于优势，选择自己信任的幕僚
which would put him in a position to select men willing to help him.
他不是俄国人
And he's not Russian.
他出生于立陶宛，由他当渔夫的祖父养大
He's Lithuanian by birth, raised by his paternal grandfather, a fisherman.
他也没有子女，无后顾之忧
And he has no children, no ties to leave behind.
今天还是他妻子逝世一周年的纪念日
And today is the first anniversary of his wife's death.
得了吧
Come on.
你只是个分析师，难道真能看穿他的心思？
You're just an analyst. How can you read his mind?
我了解雷米思，将军
I know Ramius, General.
他是潜艇界的传奇人物
He's nearly a legend in the submarine community.
他也不是个乖乖牌
He's been a maverick his entire career.
我曾在使馆晚宴上见过他一次
I actually met him once at an embassy dinner.
你见过雷米思舰长吗，将军？
Have you ever met Captain Ramius, General?
霍利斯将军…
Admiral Hollis,
距离雷米思到达能向我们发射导弹的位置还有多久？
how long before Ramius could be in a position to fire his missiles at us?
四天
Four days.
好，我会向总统作简报
All right. I'll brief the President.
会议到此结束，先生们
That will be all, gentlemen.
莱恩博士
Dr. Ryan,
能否请你留下来一下？
would you stay for a moment, please?
我只是要你说出自己的想法，但是老天…
I said speak your mind, Jack, but Jesus...
杰克，你刚刚让将军很没面子
You slammed the door on the general pretty hard, Jack.
我不是有意的，长官
That was not my intention, sir.
你当然是有意的
Yes, it was.
他故意讽刺你，所以你要教训他
He was patronizing you, and you stomped on him.
在我看来是他活该
In my opinion, he deserved it.
听着
Listen,
我是一名政客，这意味着我擅于说谎伪装
I'm a politician, which means I'm a cheat and a liar,
为了达到目的
and when I'm not kissing babies,
我可以不择手段
I'm stealing their lollipops,
但这也意味着…
but it also means...
我会听取各方意见
that I keep my options open.
那么…
So...
假设你刚才的看法是对的
let's assume for a minute that you're right...
这个俄国人的确想要叛变
and this Russian intends to defect.
你认为我们该怎么办？
What do you suggest we do about it?
当然是接管潜艇，长官
We definitely grab the boat, sir.
等一下
Wait a minute.
我们说的可不是投诚的米格机
We're not talking about some stray pilot with a MIG.
我们是在讨论
We're talking about...
价值几十亿美元苏联的财产
several billion dollars' worth of Soviet state property.
他们肯定想要夺回来
They're going to want it back.
也许到时候
Maybe it's enough then
派几个人登舰检查
just to get some people onboard and inspect it.
可以随便想个名目
Call it whatever you want to...
例如海岸警卫队的安全检查
A coast guard safety inspection.
那要怎么进行？
So how do we proceed?
首先，我们应该通知大西洋司令部
First, we need to contact the commanders in the Atlantic directly.
如果让苏联方面听到风声
The Russians get one whiff of this through the regular communications circuits,
这戏就没得唱了
the game is up.
其次，我们必须搞清楚如何帮他们
Second, we figure out how we can help them.
想法介入其中
We devise a plan to intercede,
必须是能立刻执行的计划
ready to go at a moment's notice.
最后，想办法和雷米思取得联系
Third, somebody's got to go make contact with Ramius
查看他真正的意图
and find out what his intentions really are.
好，你何时出发？
Okay. When do you leave?
等等
Wait a minute.
将军说的对
The general was right.
我不是这方面专家，我只是个分析师
I am not field personnel. I am only an analyst.
你是最好的人选
You're perfect.
我没其他人可以用
I can't ask any of these characters to go.
没人相信这个说法
They don't believe in it.
他们也不会拿自己前途开玩笑，但你…
They'd never stake their reputation on a hunch, whereas you...
可以被牺牲
Are expendable.
差不多
Something like that.
我给你三天的时间来证明你的理论
I'll give you three days to prove your theory correct.
在那之后
After that,
我必须要追捕雷米思并杀死他
I have to hunt down Ramius and destroy him.
你同意吗？
Will you do it?
（座标5490）
（苏联阿法级潜艇科诺瓦罗夫号）
（图波列夫船长指挥）
我的天！收起桅杆！
Mother of God! Secure the mast!
三分之二全速前进！下潜至900米！
All ahead, two-thirds! Set depth to 900 meters!
怎么了？发生什么事？
What is it? What's happened?
桅杆收起，加速前进
Mast secured, helm at two-thirds.
朝航道205前进
Commence heading 2-0-5.
2-0-5, affirmative.
这些命令是七小时前发出的
These orders are seven bloody hours old!
被压在一堆文件的下面
Sitting on the bottom like an addled schoolboy.
- 舰长  - 我们正经过…
- Captain... - Passing at...
- 侧翼，全速前进  - 侧翼，全速前进
- All ahead, flank. - All ahead, flank.
问问轮机室
Inquire of the engineer about the possibility
航速可否加快到105
of going to 105% on the reactor.
七个小时
Seven hours.
整个舰队都在追捕他
The entire fleet is after him.
- 深度900米  - 很好
- Leveling at 900 meters. - Very well.
船长
Captain,
机械师说航速可以加到105
engineer reports 105% on the reactor possible,
但并不建议那样做
but not recommended.
加速至105
Go to 105 on the reactor.
舰长，发生了什么事？我们要去哪？
Captain, what is it? Where are we going?
我们要去消灭一个朋友，叶甫根尼
We're going to kill a friend, Yevgeni.
我们要去灭掉雷米思
We're going to kill Ramius.
如果你喜欢罗宋汤
If you like borscht, perhaps,
我在一艘邮轮上尝过更棒的
but I've eaten better in an oiler's galley.
我妻子对侍者说
My wife said to the waiter,
“他是从哪学的烹饪，是阿富汗吗？”
"Where did this man learn to cook, Afghanistan?"
然后我们去了大剧院，欣赏芭蕾舞
So then we went on to the Bolshoi, the ballet,
去看那名新来的女舞者，她真的很漂亮
to see this new girl as Giselle. You remember how beautiful she was.
听说嫁给了一位厂长…
She just married a factory manager.
恕我打断一下，医官
Excuse me, Doctor.
你有最新的辐射测试数据吗？
Do you have the figures for the latest batch of radiation tests?
- 现在就要吗？  - 现在就要
- Now? - Now.
若有上次的数据那更好
Perhaps you could bring the preceding set as well
可以做比较
for comparison.
谢谢你，医官
Thank you, Doctor.
这些事可以绊住他
It will take him some time.
舰长，在开始之前
Before we begin, Captain,
我想知道普汀是怎么死的
I'd like to know exactly what happened to Putin.
他不是滑倒暴毙的吧？
He didn't slip on his tea, did he?
我不喜欢你的口气，史拉文
I don't think I like your tone, Slavin.
我的语气怎么了？
What the hell's my tone got to do with it?
我们是在冒生命危险
We're risking our lives here.
普汀只会为我们制造麻烦
Putin could've caused complications.
你认为他知道我们的计划后
Did you think he would just go away and sulk
会无动于衷吗？
while we carried out our plans?
你是说他是被谋杀的？
Are you saying he was murdered?
- 我的天  - 别吵，尤里
- My God. - Stop whining, Yuri.
- 你要如何证明是谋杀？  - 那么那是真的罗？
- How can you justify murder? - So he was murdered.
我对这件事没什么意见
I have no opinion.
他就是一头猪
The man was a pig,
但事前应该跟我们商量一下
but it's a decision we should've all made together.
你无权在这发号施令
You are not in command here.
如果被其他人发现，恐怕会有人叛变
If the crew finds out, we could have a mutiny.
- 你说什么？  - 他们会把我们全部杀死
- What are you talking about? - They could kill us all.
现在是牵一发而动全身
Everything that happens on this ship affects us all.
军械长已经开始怀疑了
The Master-at-Arms is already suspicious.
我们还可以回头
We could still go back.
没有回头的余地了
There will be no going back.
在我们出发前
Before we sailed,
我寄了一封信给帕多林将军
I dispatched a letter to Admiral Padorin,
信中告诉他们我们意图叛变
in which I announced our intention to defect.
你为什么那样做？
In the name of God, why?
当他抵达新大陆后
When he reached the New World,
柯德便将船烧毁
Cortez burned his ships.
结果
As a result,
他手下的士兵大受鼓舞
his men were well motivated.
你这是帮我们判了死刑
You have signed our death warrants.
帕多林会发动整个舰队
Padorin will send the entire fleet.
他们一定会找到我们的
Jesus, they'll find us.
一旦被找到…
They'll find us and...
没有人会找到我们，别再说了
No one's going to find us. That's enough, Yuri.
你非得这么做？
You had to do it,
不能就这样把潜艇移交到美国人手中？
you couldn't just turn the submarine over to the Americans.
而非得做出一份政治声明？
You had to make a political statement.
或是还有其他理由，舰长
Or was it something deeper, Captain,
让你非要用这么激烈的手段吗？
something that made you unable to slip away?
是自我主义作祟吗？舰长
Was it ego, Captain?
我们都有自己的理由，维克特
We each have our reasons, Victor.
当我看到这艘舰艇的蓝图时
My own began the day I was handed the blueprints for this ship,
我知道这潜艇是为开战而制
a ship which had but one use.
至于其他原因
And as for the rest,
恕我不便奉告
those are things that I alone must carry the burden for.
阿纳托利，你是在害怕我们的舰队？
Anatoli, you're afraid of our fleet.
你是该怕
You should be.
我个人认为我们有三分之一的成功机会
Personally, I give us one chance in three.
谁还要茶？
More tea, anyone?
都不要？
No?
那就可以回去你们的岗位了
Then you may report back to your posts.
你们都听见了，解散
You heard the Captain. Dismissed.
舰长
Captain.
舰长，我不会在别人面前反对你
Captain, I would never disagree with you in front of the men,
你知道
you know that.
但维克特说的对
But in this case, Victor is right.
将此事通知莫斯科当局并不妥
It would've been better if you had not informed Moscow.
瓦西里
Vasily.
不用害怕莫斯科
Moscow is not the worry,
也不用担心整个苏联海军
nor the whole Soviet navy.
我知道他们的战略
I know their tactics.
这点我占优势
I have the advantage.
不
No.
值得担心的是美国人
The worry is the Americans.
如果我们能碰对人
If we meet the right sort,
策略就会成功
this will work.
如果找错人…
We get some buckaroo...
有乱流，长官
Some turbulence, Commander?
你讨厌坐飞机吧
You don't like flying.
真不算什么
This is nothing!
我们五个月前还碰过更强的乱流
You should've been with us five, six months ago!
说到了呕吐
You talk about puke!
我们在日本海上空遇到暴风云团
We ran into a hailstorm over the Sea of Japan, right?
大家把胆汁都吐出来了！
Everybody's retching their guts out!
机长把午餐全吐到挡风玻璃上
The pilot shot his lunch all over the windshield,
我则是吐到无线电上
and I barf on the radio!
全都吐得一干二净
Knocked it out completely,
呕吐物的重量可不轻！
and it wasn't that lightweight stuff either!
增加了不少负担！
It was that chunky, industrial-weight puke!
你想要尝一口吗？
You want a bite?
杰克，下次再有好点子时记在备忘录里
Jack, next time you get a bright idea, just put it in a memo.
（美国海军企业号航空母舰）
（北大西洋  新斯科细亚省东部）
长官
Sir.
没事了，上尉，谢谢你
That'll be all, Lieutenant. Thank you.
从魏蒙来的飞机？
That hawkeye from Weymouth Trap?
途中遇到强烈的乱流
Four wire. Caught a gust over the fantail.
运气还不错
Not bad, considering.
有位先生专程来见你
The gentleman is here to see you.
先生？
The gentleman?
你到底说什么呢，查理？
What the hell you talking about, Charlie?
抱歉穿了你们的军服，长官
I apologize for the uniform, sir.
格里尔将军希望此事能低调处理
This is Admiral Greer's idea of a low profile.
你为吉姆格里尔工作
You work for Jim Greer?
对，长官
That's right, sir.
你能否告诉我这是怎么一回事
Then I imagine you'll tell me what all the hubbub's about.
舰长，你有空吗？
Captain, you got a minute?
琼斯有事要报告
Jonesy's got something I think you ought to see.
马丁，去喝杯咖啡
Martinez, get yourself a cup of coffee.
- 再给我倒杯茶上来  - 是，舰长
- Send me up some tea. - Aye, Captain.
传令兵，给舰长倒杯茶来
Messenger, get the captain a cup of tea.
舰长
Captain.
长官
Sir,
记得我说我听到歌声的事吗？
the moment that sub went silent and I thought I heard some singing,
我从背景听到些很微弱的声音
I heard something in the background real faint.
跟丢潜艇之后，我又听到了
After all those subs took off, I caught it again,
并把声音录了下来
and got it on tape.
我在电脑上处理过了
I washed it through the computer
并把这个声音分离出来
and was able to isolate this sound.
电脑分析出来的结果是
When I asked the computer to identify it,
岩浆断层
what I got was magma displacement.
长官，声纳分析仪
You see, sir, the SAPS software
最初就是用来监测地震的
was originally written to look for seismic events.
当仪器感到困惑时，有点像…
I think when it gets confused, it kind of...
跑回家找妈妈
runs home to mama.
琼斯，我不太明白你的意思
I'm not following you, Jonesy.
对不起，长官
Sir, I'm sorry.
用十倍速来听
Listen to it at 10 times speed.
那是人为的声音，舰长
Now, that's got to be manmade, Captain.
好吧
All right.
第一次信号是在9点15分
The first contact was at 09:15,
方位269
and the bearing was 2-6-9.
九点半时它在这里
At 09:30, it was here.
11点和11点15分时
I came back to it at 11:00 and 11:15,
分别是在这里和这里
here and here.
记得苏联潜艇
Remember the dispatch we got about Russian sub skippers
曾以高速通过雷克屋脊
running the Reykjanes Ridge at high speeds
因为他们拥有高精度的水下峡谷监测设备
because they had hyper-accurate surveys of the underwater canyons?
索尔断崖正是那些峡谷的主要入口
The front door to those canyons was a formation called Thor's Twins.
怎么了？
Yeah?
（失去信号）
（索尔断崖）
看着
Look at that.
- 正好是一号红色路线  - 舰长
- Right into Red Route One. - Captain.
你可能觉得我疯了
You may think I'm crazy,
我敢打赌那个岩浆断层
but I'll bet that magma displacement
就是某种新型的俄国潜艇
was actually some new Russian sub,
而且正朝冰岛前进
and it's headed for the Iceland coast.
我有没有听错，琼斯？
Have I got this straight, Jonesy?
一台价值四千万的电脑
A $40 million computer
告诉你说那是地震
tells you you're chasing an earthquake,
然而你不信
but you don't believe it,
却凭自己的主观臆断？
and you come up with this on your own?
- 是，长官  - 你还有其他的航行数据吗？
- Yes, sir. - Including all the navigation math?
- 长官，我掌握了所有…  - 别紧张，我信你
- Sir, I've got all the... - Relax, Jonesy. You sold me.
汤米，你马上策划一条最快路线
Tommy, I want you to plot us a speed course
到达红色一线的底部
for the bottom end of Red Route One.
进峡谷后我们就追不到它了
We'll never find him in those canyons.
首先上升到了望深度
First take us to periscope depth.
看有没有讯息传进来
This we got to phone in.
是，船长
Aye, aye, Captain.
等等，琼斯
Hang on, Jonesy.
如果距离拉近
If I can get you close enough,
你有办法辨别潜艇方位吗？
can you track this sucker?
是，长官
Yes, sir.
我已经知道应该追踪什么声音，我一定会抓住他的
Now that I know what to listen for, I'll bag him.
- 回去岗位吧  - 是，长官
- Carry on. - Yes, sir.
那是我听说过的最疯狂的事
That's the craziest notion I've ever heard.
现役军官？
A serving line officer?
带着一整艘潜艇？
An entire ballistic missile submarine?
不可能所有人都想叛变
They can't all want to defect.
就只有军官想变节，也令人难以相信
Even if it's only the officers, it's extremely difficult to believe.
他有何计划？
What's his plan?
计划？
His plan?
俄国人喜欢依计划行事
Russians don't take a dump, son, without a plan.
高级将领不会未经深思熟虑
Senior captains don't start something this dangerous
就贸然采取行动
without having thought the matter through.
是不是他打算
What's he going to do,
将潜艇直接驶进纽约，说他想投诚吧？
sail into New York, pop the hatch, and say here I am?
可能就是那么简单
It might be just that simple, yes.
若只牵涉到中央情报局，事情也许会很简单
Things may appear simple in the cubicle at CIA,
但是在大西洋上
but in the middle of the Atlantic
有一票苏联舰艇正虎视眈眈
with Soviet warships bearing down on us,
情况就会变得很复杂
they get more complex.
- 来根烟吗？  - 不用了，谢谢
- Smoke? - No, thank you.
而且我认为登舰检查
And I don't think your notion of a few days' inspection
这个主意也行不通
is going to wash either.
要对该潜艇有相当的研究成果
In order to be of any value, you'd have to tear it apart.
必需花费数月的时间
The metallurgy would take a couple of months.
那么我们就必须扣住潜艇
Then we'd have to keep it.
你怎么处置那些船员呢？
What will you do with the crew?
不想变节的人回去后
Ones that don't defect will go back
会说是我们扣住潜艇
and say we got the boat.
你打算杀死他们？
Or do you plan to eliminate them?
我们这不是在打仗，长官
We're not at war, sir.
唯一的办法就是让这些人离开潜艇
So you have to get them off the boat in such a way
别让他们知道潜艇被扣留
that they think we don't have it,
这些人遣返后也会说潜艇不在我们手上
and they'll report that we don't have it to their bosses.
否则计划根本不会成功
Otherwise, this whole business is just academic, right?
是，长官，我完全同意你的看法
Yes, sir. I think I see your point.
你多久没睡了？
When's the last time you slept?
有一阵子了
A while.
参谋长会带你去休息一会
The chief outside will fix you up.
谢谢你，长官
Thank you, sir.
舰长
Captain.
到天亮还有几个小时
It'll be dawn in a couple of hours.
我们在指挥中心等你
We'll be in the CIC.
这次似乎有点失去控制了
Things are liable to get a little dicey around here.
没错，长官
Yes, sir.
你认为他是不是疯了？
You think he's crazy?
肯定是
Certifiable.
我不管他的地位有多高
No matter what his credentials,
我还是不喜欢他穿着海军制服
I don't care for him wearing the uniform.
你看到他手上的戒指了吗？
Did you see that ring on his finger?
他是海军陆战队72级的成员
The academy, class of '72. A Marine.
你开玩笑
You're kidding.
- 你怎么知道…  - 格里尔告诉我的
- How did you... - Greer told me.
三年级的暑假
Summer of his third year,
他在一场直升机失事中受伤
he went down in a chopper accident.
所有其他组员都殉难
Bad. Pilot and crew killed.
他花了十个月进行复健
That kid spent 10 months in traction...
又用了一年才重新学会走路
and another year learning to walk again.
他在医院里完成了第四年的学业
He did his fourth year from the hospital.
你看着办吧，查理
It's up to you, Charlie,
不过我希望你能对他客气些
but you might consider cutting the kid a little slack.
反正苏联舰队也会在我们之前找到它
Russians are going to find that sub before we get near it, anyway.
长官，我们正通过索尔断崖
Passing Thor's Twins, sir.
很好
Very good.
舰长，现在我们正通过索尔断崖
Passing the Twins now, Captain.
很好，你可以展开行动了
Very good. You may commence your run.
到第一个弯道时再告诉我
Call me at the first turning.
是的，舰长
Aye, Captain.
卡玛若夫
Mr. Kamarov.
- 你现在可以展开行动了  - 是，长官
- You may commence your run now. - Aye, sir.
听我指令行进第一航程
First leg on my mark,
航道260
course 2-6-0.
航速18节
Speed, 18 knots.
深度270米
Depth, 270 meters.
五、四、三、二、一
Five, four, three, two, one.
行动
Mark.
控制室，航道260
Diving command, course 2-6-0.
- 航道260  - 航速18节
- Course 2-6-0, aye. - Speed, 18 knots.
航速18节
Speed, 18 knots, aye.
别这么胆小，尤里
Stop pissing, Yuri.
把表和地图给我
Give me a stopwatch and a map,
我闭着眼都能飞越阿尔卑斯山
and I'll fly the Alps in a plane with no windows.
但是地图必须很精准
If the map is accurate enough.
我们已经靠近第一个弯道
We're in the lane and approaching first turn.
30秒后左转航道195
Come left to course 1-9-5.
上升至200米
In 30 seconds, decrease depth to 200 meters.
航速不变
Maintain speed.
很好，引航员
Very good, Navigator.
舰长，我们正接近第一个弯道
Captain, we're approaching the first turn.
25秒后转向航道195
Twenty-five seconds to course 1-9-5.
加速至26节
Increase speed to 26 knots...
重新计算
and recompute.
是，舰长
Aye, Captain.
引航员，航速26节，重新计算
Navigator, recompute for 26 knots.
准备开始
Turn on my mark.
五、四、三、二、一
Five, four, three, two, one.
行动
Mark.
控制室，左转航道195
Diving control, come left to 1-9-5.
- 仰角左转  - 左转195
- Come left to 1-9-5. - Up on the bow planes.
航道195，航速保持…
Course now 1-9-5 and maintaining speed...
26节
26 knots.
卡玛若夫
Mr. Kamarov?
下一航段，舰长
Next leg, Captain,
右转航道240，再过…
come right to course 2-4-0 now at...
8分40秒后
eight minutes and 40 seconds.
很好，保持航线和航速
Very good. Maintain course and speed.
太快了，瓦西里
Too fast, Vasily.
太快了
Too fast.
这些图表都是精确地列出的
Those charts are laid out precisely.
短时间内这么快的速度会造成危险
So many knots for so many seconds.
这件事太愚蠢了
And this thing handles like a pig.
说话小心点，斯拉文先生
Watch your bearing, Mr. Slavin.
15秒后转向，舰长
Fifteen seconds to turn, Captain.
- 要减速吗？  - 不要
- Should we decrease speed? - Negative.
- 准备右转  - 是，长官
- Prepare to come right. - Aye, sir.
八、七、六、五
Eight, seven, six, five,
四、三、二、一
four, three, two, one.
行动
Mark.
俯角15度
Fifteen degrees down angle on the bow planes.
右转航道240，开始转向
Come right 2-4-0. Move it!
我们在航道上了
We're in the lane.
34分钟后到达海王断层
Next leg 34 minutes to the Neptune Massif.
航道240
Course 2-4-0.
发生什么事？
What happened?
降温系统失常
The cryogenic plant!
磁石无法冷却
The magnets aren't cooling.
履带推进器温度已升高至50度，超过警戒范围
Temperature in the caterpillar is 50 degrees above red line and rising.
如果不尽快停止运作，履带会很快融化
If we don't shut down, it's going to melt.
立刻关掉！
Kill it! Shut it down!
- 舰长？  - 什么情况？
- Captain? - What happened?
降温系统失效
The cryogenic plant failed.
反应炉有损坏吗？
Reactor damage?
动力受到部分影响，不过反应炉没受到损坏
There was a power spike, but the reactor scrammed automatically.
有没有辐射外泄？
Was there any radiation leakage?
我还不清楚
I don't know yet!
- 多久能修复？  - 我先得知道出了什么问题
- How long will it take to fix? - I got to find what's wrong first.
可能是液氦出了问题，也可能是导体坏掉
Could be the liquid helium or the superconductors.
舰长，在履带推进器修复之前我们不得不停下了
Captain, we will have to stop until we can repair the caterpillar unit.
不行
Negative.
使用正常动力前进
We'll run on normal propulsion.
舰长，如此一来会发出声音
Captain, we will not be silent.
航速改为20节
Make revolutions for 20 knots...
然后启动螺旋桨
and engage the propellers.
是，舰长
Aye, Captain.
启动引擎
Commence engine start-up.
他会害死大家
He'll get us all killed.
舰长有他的道理
The Captain knows what he's doing.
医官
Doctor.
海军演习？
Naval activities?
我完全不懂海事
I have no knowledge of this.
也没当过海军
But then, I never was a sailor.
大使先生
Mr. Ambassador,
目前有100艘贵国舰艇
you have nearly 100 vessels operating
齐集大西洋上
in the North Atlantic right now.
贵国的飞机所投下的声纳浮标
Your aircraft have dropped enough sonar buoys
多得可以让人从格陵兰岛走到苏格兰
that a man could walk from Greenland to Scotland
而且脚都不会打湿
without getting his feet wet.
你别再跟我打哈哈了
Shall we dispense with the bull?
你的用辞真是委婉，皮尔特先生
You make your point as delicately as ever, Mr. Pelt,
可是…
but...
而且看似演习也可能是开战的前兆
And what looks like an exercise could be a prelude to war.
你怎么区分它们？
How can we tell the difference?
为了小心起见，我们必须检查你们的舰队
Prudence demands that we deploy ships to observe yours.
贵国政府应该知道
Your government should consider
双方舰队及战机在如此频繁的接触下
that having your ships and ours, your aircraft and ours,
如此的接近是很危险的事
in such proximity is inherently dangerous.
大使先生，战争就是那样开始的
Wars have begun that way, Mr. Ambassador.
我方有一艘潜艇失踪了
We have lost one of our submarines.
失踪了？
Lost it?
我们怀疑潜艇可能失事…
We fear she may be down, and...
这有点难以启齿，可是…
This is most embarrassing, but...
舰上有部分军官是…
Several of the officers are sons of...
高干子弟
high party officials.
还有一个是中央委员的孩子
One is even the son of a Central Committee Member.
我…
I...
不能说是谁
cannot say which.
你说这是大规模的营救行动？
You're telling me this is a massive rescue operation?
对
That is correct.
很抱歉，我们能做些什么？
I'm terribly sorry. How can we help?
我不清楚…
I'm not sure that...
或者展开一次联合营救任务？
Perhaps a joint rescue mission?
谢谢你的提议，先生
That is very gracious of you, sir.
我会向上级传达
I'll pass your offer on.
目前来看
But at this time,
我相信情况仍在我方的掌握中
I think we're doing everything that can be done.
（大熊狐步692号）
（苏联反潜机）
（冰岛南部）
舰长？
Captain?
我们根据你的意见来策划
Our strategy depends on your answer.
整个舰队都会知道我们的位置
The entire fleet will know where we are.
舰长，声纳信息
Captain, Sonar.
有艘涡轮螺旋桨潜艇在附近
We've been overflown by a multi-engine turboprop.
放到扩音器上
Put it on audio.
正从我们旁边通过
Short transients, close aboard.
排水门有东西进入
Water entry of small objects.
是声纳浮标
Sonar buoys.
- 准备应战  - 准备应战
- Battle stations. - Battle stations!
- Battle stations! - Battle stations!
还有多久到海王断层
How long to Neptune Massif?
多久？
How long?
四分十秒
Four minutes, 10 seconds.
我们要下潜吗，舰长？
Should we bottom the boat?
不，现在那样做太迟了，我们没时间了
No. Too late now. We've run out of time.
进行反制，准备发射飞弹
Countermeasures. Prepare to launch missiles.
是，长官
Aye, sir.
上方有战机出现
Aircraft on computer guidance.
请求发射炮弹
Request permission to launch.
请求照准
You are authorized to launch the weapon.
炮弹已发射
Weapon is away.
全速前进，有鱼雷接近
High speed screw! Torpedo in the water!
抓稳
Stand by.
鱼雷持续接近
Torpedo is active.
鱼雷已锁定我舰
Torpedo has acquired.
发射反鱼雷装置
Launch countermeasures.
发射反鱼雷装置，长官
Launch countermeasures. Aye, sir.
我们还在航线中
We're in the lane.
多久到达海王断层？
How long till the turn at Massif?
两分九秒
Two minutes, nine seconds.
进入峡谷后将无法避过鱼雷
We have no room to maneuver in these canyons.
- 如果反制不成功…  - 闭嘴
Shut up.
目标接近反鱼雷装置
Torpedo has reached countermeasures.
没有命中
Torpedo has lost contact.
正在接近海王断层
Massif approaching.
鱼雷重新锁定我舰
Torpedo has reacquired.
鱼雷正朝我们而来
Torpedo has reacquired and is homing.
还多久进入断层？
Give me the count.
30秒后右舵40度
Turn at Massif 40 degrees starboard in 30 seconds.
鱼雷命中时间？
Time to torpedo impact?
命中时间是35秒
Torpedo impact, 35 seconds.
- 提到高速  - 全速前进
- Increase to flank. - Full ahead flank.
- 全速前进  - 全速前进，明白
- Full ahead flank. - Full ahead flank, aye.
鱼雷40秒后命中目标
Torpedo impact now 40 seconds.
35秒
35 seconds.
30秒
30 seconds.
进入断层倒数计时
Turn at Massif in
七、六、五、四
seven, six, five, four,
三、二、一
three, two, one.
好
Mark.
鱼雷25秒后命中
Torpedo impact 25 seconds...
- 转弯吗，舰长？  - 还没
- The turn, Captain. - Not yet.
八秒后进入
Mark plus eight seconds.
9秒、10秒、11秒、12秒
Plus nine, plus 10 seconds, plus 11, plus 12,
13秒、14秒、15秒
plus 13 seconds, plus 14, plus 15 seconds.
舰长，我们不宜偏离航道这么远
Captain, we're out of position by a boat length.
鱼雷15秒后命中
Torpedo impact now 15 seconds.
发出警报
Sound collision.
我们偏离航线了
We're out of the lane!
- 回去岗位上  - 伯罗丁？
- You're relieved. - Borodin?
右满舵！全速右转！
Right full rudder! Reverse starboard engine!
右满舵，全速右转
Right full rudder. All back starboard shaft.
全速倒退
All back starboard shaft!
鱼雷12秒后命中
Torpedo impact 12 seconds,
十、九、八、七、六、五
10, nine, eight, seven, six, five...
舰长
Captain,
- 他们真的向我们开炮了！  - 镇静！
- they're really shooting at us! - Pull yourself together!
为什么？
Why?
冷静点，孩子
Boy! Easy, boy.
如果我们真的被击中
If they were really shooting at us,
我们现在已经死了
we'd be dead by now.
给我一个解释
Give me some line.
我找出履带推进器故障的原因了
I found out what happened to the caterpillar.
是缓冲线路遭破坏
The buffer circuit has been torn out.
故障是迟早的事
It was only a matter of time...
毕竟是超负荷运载
before an overload shut it down.
你说什么？
What are you saying?
不管是谁，他知道如何破坏
Whoever did this knew how to cripple
这个不容易发现的履带推进器
the caterpillar in a way not easy to find.
舰长，我们的舰上有间谍
Captain, we have a saboteur on board.
不可能是军官
It can't be any of the officers.
否则早在出海前他就行动了
They had plenty of time before we embarked.
肯定是船员
Must be a crew member.
到普汀的舱房去
Go to Putin's cabin.
查一下船员资料
Check his files for information on the crew.
要想办法让他们离舰
We may have to put them off before we planned.
俄国人喜欢依计划行事
The average russky, son, don't take a dump without a plan.
等一下
Wait a minute.
根本不用我们操心，他会想办法
We don't have to get the crew off the sub.
他势必要这么做
He would have had to do that.
我们只需要想他会怎么做
We just have to figure out what he's going to do.
他要如何让船员离开潜艇？
How is he going to get them off the sub?
而且是自愿离舰
They'd have to want to get off.
怎么让船员自愿离开潜艇？
How do you get a crew to want to get off a submarine?
怎么能让船员自愿离开一艘核潜艇…
How do you get them to want to get off a nuclear sub...
我知道他的计划了，将军
I know how he's going to evacuate the sub.
我现在没时间，杰克
Not now, Jack.
呼叫洋基一号，请覆述一遍
Yankee One star base, say again status.
请求紧急支援
Declare an emergency.
洋基一号，请求无线电导航
Yankee One, requesting vectors.
航线270，加快速度
Vector 2-7-0 speed is buster.
洋基一号飞机液压失常
Yankee One's losing hydraulic pressure.
覆述一遍，洋基一号
Say again, Yankee One.
一架银狐战机离编队距离太近
Bear Foxtrot got too close to the group.
其中一架F14试着隔开它，结果两机相撞
One of the F-14s crowded him, and they bumped.
飞机液压失常
He's losing hydraulic fluid.
航管正试着引导他落地
They're trying to get him back aboard now.
忙碌的早晨
Busy morning.
一群俄国攻击潜艇已经进驻大西洋东岸
Russian attack subs are now stationed off every east coast port.
我们在这里
We're up here.
纽泽西号正沿着海岸行进
The New Jersey is moving up the coast
苏联除出动超过100架银狐外
while the Russians, aside from over 100 Bear Foxtrots,
还有多艘作战潜艇及海上舰队
have a row of subs and several surface groups.
他们的火力太强了
That's a lot of firepower.
对营救队伍来说，是的
For a rescue team, yes.
还有可疑的情况
There's something else strange.
他们好像正在利用声纳系统寻找些什么
They're using sonar as if they're looking for something,
- 但是却没人监听  - 什么意思？
- but nobody's listening. - What do you mean?
舰队的航速已接近30节
The rate close to 30 knots.
而那样的速度发出的声音可以摧毁我女儿的立体音响
At their speed they could run over my daughter's stereo and not hear it.
他们不是在寻找雷米思，而是在驱赶他
They're not searching for Ramius. They're driving him.
把他赶到哪去？
Driving him where?
就像猎犬紧追猎物一样
The hounds to the hunters.
你的舰长准备向美国投诚是吗，莱恩先生？
Your sub captain's going to make it to America.
他可能壮志未酬身先死
He's going to die within sight of it.
他的指挥官一直请求开火
His wing man kept requesting permission to fire.
一个不小心
Somebody messes up,
就可能爆发前所未有的海战
we'll be in the biggest naval battle since the Jutland.
天啊！
Jesus!
海水太冷了，无法驱逐他
Water's too cold to eject him.
苏联空军想把它逼上水面
Air boss will try to bring him aboard.
请问这艘是谁的潜艇？
Sir, what's this sub off by herself?
巴特曼库索的潜艇
Bart Mancuso's boat.
他将要去红色一线
He's going to the bottom of Red Route One.
他断断续续的收到一些岩浆断层的信号
He's had intermittent contact with a magma displacement.
- 他…  - 岩浆断层？
- He's got this... - Magma displacement?
像地震异常？
Is that like a seismic anomaly?
我想是，怎么了？
I suppose so. Why?
你能送我上达拉斯号吗？
Is there a way you could get me onboard the Dallas?
去干什么？
What for?
我认为曼库索舰长已经发现了红色十月
I think Mancuso's found the Red October.
他什么都没发现，杰克
He hasn't found anything, Jack.
他只是在等待
He's just waiting.
不确定他听到…
Not sure what he hear...
这套无声推进系统
Sir, this silent propulsion system
很容易被误认为…
could easily be mistaken for something...
只有直升机能送你上达拉斯号
The only way to get you onto Dallas is to fly you out to a chopper.
是把你送到最北部的唯一方法
The only way to get you that far north
而且必须用飞快的速度才能赶上
is to use a chopper turned into a flying gas can.
将军
Admiral,
洋基一号即将落地，救援人员已经就位
Yankee One is on final. Rescue personnel are in place.
提拉高左翼，你太偏左了
Pick up your left wing. You're drifting left.
提升动力！
Power, power!
机头拉高…
Wave off, wave off!
快弹出
Eject, eject, eject!
着火了、着火了！飞行甲板起火了！
Fire, fire! Fire on the flight deck!
这件事将要失控了
This business will get out of control,
一旦失去控制，大家只有自求多福了
and we'll be lucky to live through it.
飞行甲板起火了，所有人员前来帮忙
Fire on the flight deck. All hands lend assistance.
飞机有足够的燃料把你送到那里
The bird's loaded down with enough fuel to get you there,
但达拉斯号有可能不在那了
but Dallas may not be there.
我们会试着通知它
We're trying to reach her.
但如深度太深他们还是收不到
If she's gone deep, it's dodgy.
如果你必须要迫降…
If you have to ditch...
如果你必须在海上迫降
If you have to ditch,
记得打开救生衣
don't think about anything but the survival gear.
在这种温度下，你只能撑四分钟
At this water's temperature, you'll have about four minutes.
我会尽量牢记
I'll try to remember that.
杰克，下次写一份该死的备忘录
Next time, Jack, write a goddamn memo.
下潜深度650米
Diving officer, make your depth 6-5-0 feet.
深度650米
Make my depth 6-5-0 feet.
声纳连接隔热层下面的信号
Sonar, Conn preceding below the thermal layer.
- 船长睡觉了吧？  - 是的
- The captain's sacked out? - Yeah.
附加行进5,000磅
Auxiliaries proceed 5,000 pounds.
他呢？
What about him?
他不会离开的
He won't leave.
声纳，等等
Conn. Sonar, hold.
航道295没有潜艇踪迹
No contacts on bearing 2-9-5.
跟你说
You know,
有一次我看到美人鱼
I seen me a mermaid once.
我还看到鲨鱼吃章鱼的画面
I've even seen me a shark eat a octopus,
但我从未见过俄国幽灵潜艇
but I ain't never seen no phantom Russian submarine.
我们正驶出航道，船长
We're emerging from the route, Captain.
缓冲装置已经启动
I've ordered a routine clearing of the baffles.
几分钟后我们将进入第一个转弯
We'll be making the first turn in a few minutes.
履带推进器正在运转
The caterpillar is operational and...
看起来运转正常
appears to be running normally.
船员们…
The crew...
知道了间谍的事
know about the saboteur.
他们都很害怕
They are afraid.
到时候这一点会很受用
That could be useful when the time comes.
我们将在16小时后到达拉布拉多海岸
You know, we could make the Labrador Coast in 16 hours.
在得到救援之前他们就会被先冻死
Half of them would freeze before they were rescued.
不行，去麻萨诸塞或缅因州
No, it's Massachusetts or Maine...
48小时后
In 48 hours.
两天
Two days.
他们会让我住在蒙大拿吗？
Do you think they will let me live in Montana?
他们会让你住在任何你想要居住的地方
I would think they'll let you live wherever you want.
好
Good.
我就住在蒙大拿
Then I will live in Montana,
我要娶一个丰满的美国女人
and I will marry a round American woman...
我还要养兔子
and raise rabbits,
让她把兔子煮熟了给我吃
and she will cook them for me,
我还要买一台小卡车
and I will have a pickup truck.
或是…
Or a...
可能是一辆野营旅游车…
Possibly even a recreational vehicle
开着它到各个州去兜风
and drive from state to state.
- 他们会让你那样做吗？  - 当然
- Do they let you do that? - Yes.
不用打报告？
No papers?
不需要，行动自由
No papers. State to state.
好，开始转向
All right. Commence your turn.
那之后…
And then...
冬天我要住在…
in winter I will live in...
亚历桑那州
Arizona.
我觉得我应该娶两个老婆
Actually, I think I will need two wives.
至少两个
At least.
目标可能转向
Possible aspect change on target.
收到
Sonar, Conn. Aye.
同时方位变动率显示目标正在急转
Concur possible target zig based on bearing rate.
- 声纳！大回转  - 停止前进！保持安静
- Conn! Sonar! Crazy Ivan! - All stop! Quick quiet!
- 停止前进  - 引擎全部停止工作了
- All stop, aye. - Engine's all stopped.
发生了什么事，琼斯？
What's going on, Jonesy?
俄国的船长有时会突然转向
Russian captains sometimes turn suddenly
来确认后面是否有人跟踪
to see if anyone's behind them.
我们称之为大回转
We call it Crazy Ivan.
你唯一能做的就是静止不动
The only thing you can do is go dead,
关闭所有引擎
shut everything down,
在水底静止不动
and make like a hole in the water.
其中有什么蹊跷呢？
So what's the catch?
问题就是，像这么大的潜艇不可能立即刹住
Catch is a boat this big doesn't exactly stop on a dime.
如果我们太接近了，会从后面撞上它
If we're too close, we'll drift right into the back of him.
你呢？你是怎么打算的？
What about you? What do you look forward to?
我…
I...
我没有那些欲望
I have no such appetites.
看看他能否听到我们
Now, let's see if he can hear us.
你肯定有些想法的
There must be something.
是什么？
What is it?
我怀念小时候
I miss the peace of fishing
钓鱼的那种平静
like when I was a boy.
我在大海中生活了40年
Forty years I have been at sea.
钻研海上战术
A war at sea.
但没真正打过仗
A war with no battles.
没有丰碑
No monuments.
有的只是伤害
Only casualties.
在结婚的那天太太就成了活寡妇
I widowed her the day I married her.
连她死的时候，我都不在身边
My wife died while I was at sea, you know.
安排哨兵在轮机室
Post guards in the engineering spaces.
如果那个人能介入履带推动器
If he can get to the caterpillar,
他同样可以去到更要命的地方
he can get to somewhere more vital.
- 他现在在哪，琼斯？  - 声纳信号连接
- Where is he, Jonesy? - Conn, Sonar.
目标正驶离我们的右舷遮流板
Target is now coming out of our starboard baffles.
数据显示，他正回到底层
My read is that he is returning to base course.
他回到了210航线
Concur. He's returning to course 2-1-0.
他就在我们周围
He went right around us.
再给他30秒
We'll give him another 30 seconds,
然后再进行监听
then secure from silent running.
舰长
Captain?
这是最新的信息
Here's what we got on the ELF.
- 谢谢  - 是，长官
- Thanks. - Aye, sir.
这是什么？
What is it?
难以置信
You're not going to believe this.
长官，我们即将到达返航地点
Commander, we are approaching no return.
达拉斯号显然没有接到信息
Dallas apparently hasn't gotten the message.
我们必须折返
We have to turn back for the carrier.
再等它一会儿
Give it a couple more minutes.
不行，油表已经显示油料不足
Negative. Fuel status says we turn around now.
等等，你不是应该有备用燃料吗？
Fuel status? You got a reserve, don't you?
我的备用燃料只够十分钟
I've got a 10-minute reserve,
可我不能用那些燃料，除了开战
but I'm not allowed to invade that except during war.
如果你不把我送到潜艇，那就开战了
If you don't get me on that submarine, you might have it.
给你十分钟的燃料
You got 10 minutes worth of fuel.
我们在这里再等十分钟
We stay here 10 more minutes.
上升！三点钟方向有潜艇
Mount up! I got a submarine at around 3:00.
距离大概有两英哩
About 2 miles.
好，托尼，把他吊下去
Okay, Tony, hook him up.
我现在把你放到潜艇那去
I'll be lowering you down to the submarine now.
给你八分钟时间
Give me eight minutes.
希望飞机可以在烟气上飞行
Let's hope this thing runs on fumes.
很好，把潜艇浮到水面上去
Very well. Surface the ship.
浮上水面，长官
Surface the ship. Aye, sir.
不管这个人是谁，胆子真大
Whoever this guy is, he's in for one hell of a ride.
长官，往前点，坐下
Okay, Commander, go ahead and sit down.
你以前这样做过吗？
You ever do this before?
在夏威夷，但当时风平浪静
Once. On a calm day off Hawaii.
没有参照点，飞行员会停下来一段时间
The pilot will have a difficult time keeping steady.
小心雷击 把棒子拿在你身前
Don't take chances getting grounded. Keep that rod in front of you.
在这样的天气里
In air like this,
旋翼会释放出很多静电
the rotors will put out enough static electricity
可以点亮整个芝加哥
to light up Chicago.
那就是我加入海军的原因
That's why I joined the Navy.
救生舱有一名潜水员待命，以防他掉进大海
A diver's in the escape trunk in case this guy goes in the drink.
这人一定是疯了
Someone must have a burr up his ass
才会做出这样惊险的举动
to go for a stunt like this.
好，准备！弄好你的h子
All right. Ready! Ready! Get your hook up!
长官，如果我想要把你拉起来
Commander, if I got to bring you back up,
我就晃动绳索，像这样给你一个大拇指
I'm going to shake the wire. I'll give you a thumbs up, like this.
双臂交叉，明白了吗？出去吧
Remember to cross your arms. Got it? Okay. Out you go.
乘客出了舱门
Passenger's out the door.
乘客正在下降，向前行驶
Passenger's halfway down, drifting forward. Start forward.
汤米，把钩子钩到他的绳索上
All right, Tommy. Get the hook on his cable.
小心点
On his cable. Now, watch it.
别碰他，他过来了
Don't touch him. Okay, here he comes.
不
No!
风势太强了
It would be easier without that bloody crosswind.
他去哪了？我看不到他了
Where is he? I can't see him.
别碰他
Don't touch him!
杰克！杰克！杰克！
Jack! Jack! Jack!
这样不行
This is never going to work.
把他拉回来
Okay, reel him back in.
托尼，后面的情况如何…
Tony, what's going on back...
什么情况？达拉斯号，你们有救生人员吗？
What happened? Dallas, have you got a swimmer standing?
紧急状况，有人落水了！
Emergency stop! Man overboard!
左舷！派出潜水员
Port side! Send out the diver!
达拉斯号，我们必须返航
Very well, Dallas. We are history.
快叫医生下来！我会在逃生舱
Get the doc down here! I'll be in the escape trunk.
下梯！让开
Down ladder! Down ladder! Make a hole!
注意他的头，注意他的头
Watch his head. Watch his head.
你好吗，舰长？
How do you do, Captain?
很荣幸登上了潜艇
It's a pleasure to be aboard.
我必须和总统谈谈
I have to talk to the President.
当然
Of course.
我能问一下你想谈什么吗？
May I inquire as to the subject?
先前那份报告称我们的一艘潜艇丢了
It seems that the initial reports that one of our submarines was missing
那个消息并不完全正确
were not completely accurate.
那艘有问题的潜艇
The submarine in question
是由马可・雷米思舰长所指挥
is commanded by Captain Marko Ramius.
很显然，他的精神状况…
Apparently, he has suffered a kind of...
出了些问题
mental or nervous breakdown.
在他起航之前
Just before he sailed,
他寄了封信给尤里・帕多林将军
he posted a letter to Admiral Yuri Padorin
他在信中宣称他打算…
in which he announced his intention to...
向美国发射导弹
To fire his missiles on the United States.
你上次怎么没告诉我？
Why didn't you tell me this the last time we met?
以我的地位来说
In my position I'm sometimes compromised
莫斯科方面不会把什么情况都告诉我
by the fact Moscow doesn't always tell me everything.
所以说是你们的一位舰长精神错乱了？
So one of your submarine captains has gone insane?
你要我们怎么做？
What do you want from us?
需要贵国的援助
You offered your assistance.
本来是营救任务
That was a rescue mission.
现在你是希望我们找到他并杀死他
Now you want us to help you hunt him down and kill him.
我正是因这件事被指派来询问你们的总统
I have been instructed to ask your president for precisely that.
找他？我们已经发现他了
Find him? We already found him.
为弄你上来我们不得不停下
We had to break off to pick you up.
- 舰长打断一下，咖啡？  - 谢谢
- Captain, excuse me. Coffee? - Thank you.
- 来根烟吗？  - 我不吸烟
- Cigarette? - Don't smoke.
假设我们找到他了
Assuming we can find him,
我们到底该怎么做？
just what exactly am I supposed to do about it?
舰长
Captain, radio.
通讯室收到一封紧急电报
We're receiving flash traffic on the VLF emergency circuit.
很好，把它弄下来
Very well. Bring it down.
说吧，莱恩先生？
Mr. Ryan?
长官，你们先出去一下
Chief, excuse us for a second.
莱奥，出去吧
Leonard, come on out of there.
我们跟踪的潜艇叫做红色十月
The sub we're after is called the Red October.
是由一个叫雷米思的人指挥的
She's under the command of a man named Ramius.
现在有可能他…
Now, there's the possibility that he...
和大部分船员打算叛变
and a good portion of his crew are attempting to defect.
叛变？
Defect?
失陪一下
Excuse me.
你说那艘潜艇是红色十月号？
You say the boat's called the Red October?
- 对  - 舰长叫雷米思？
- That's right. - Skipper's Ramius?
对
Right.
情况似乎有变化，莱恩先生
It seems the circumstances have changed somewhat, Mr. Ryan.
给这个人拿些干衣服来
Get this man some dry clothes.
- 我在指挥舱  - 是，长官
- I'll be in the conn. - Aye, aye, sir.
“国家指挥中心”
"National Command Authority
“通知台风级苏联潜艇红色十月号”
"informed Soviet Typhoon-class submarine Red October
“有可能叛变”
"is potential renegade
“并威胁独立导弹发射系统”
"and threatens independent missile launch.
“你有权使用任何必须的力量”
"You are authorized to use any necessary force
“阻止这艘潜艇”
"to prevent said submarine
“接近美国海岸”
"from approaching the coast of the United States."
左舵10度，平稳运行在265航线上
Left 10 degrees rudder steady on course 2-6-5.
左舵10度，保持航线265
Left 10 degrees rudder secure course of 2-6-5.
航速14节
Make turns for 14 knots.
监察官，保持警戒
Chief of the watch, rig for red.
舵手和引航员到指挥舱甲板上去
Time Quartermasters and Navigator on the deck in the conn.
什么事？
What's going on?
战位准备就绪
Battle stations are manned and ready.
很好
Very well.
- 舰长，我必须要跟你谈谈  - 现在不行
- Captain, I have to talk to you. - Not now.
深度到达1200英尺，角度向下20度
Make your depth 1,200 feet, 20 degrees down angle.
潜水官，深度到达1200英尺
Diving Officer, make your depth 1,200 feet,
向下20度
20 degree down.
全速水平下潜 船尾全速水平下潜
Full dive on fair water planes. Full dive on stern planes.
向下20度
Twenty degree down.
过了450英尺，正下潜到1200英尺
Passing 450 feet, going to 1,200.
500英尺
Five hundred.
600英尺
Six hundred.
700英尺
Seven hundred.
准备好了吗？
Did you get a good fix?
- 是的，舰长  - 很好
- Yes, Captain. - Very well.
到达指定深度，1200英尺
At ordered depth, 1,200 feet.
声纳
Sonar, Conn.
你听到他了吗，琼斯？
You got him, yet, Jonesy?
很微弱，等一下
Very faint, sir. Hold on.
是的长官，在250方位联系到了台风七号
Yes, sir. Contact Typhoon 7 on bearing 2-5-0.
他就在我们预想的位置
Right where he's supposed to be.
他察觉到我们的存在了吗？
Any sign he's alerted to our presence?
没有，还是像以前一样运行
No. Operating as before.
到265航线左边
Come left 2-6-5.
悄悄跟上他，汤米
Bring us up behind him quietly, Tommy.
是，船长
Aye, aye, Captain.
潜水指挥官，深度到达500英尺
Diving Officer, make your depth 500 feet.
船长，请听我说，两分钟就足够了
Captain, please listen to me. Two minutes, that's all.
绘图员，还有多久可截获他
Plot, time to intercept his track.
四分钟，船长
Four minutes, Captain.
很好，莱恩先生，两分钟
Very well, Mr. Ryan. Two minutes.
我知道你被授命攻击这很合理
It makes perfect sense.
看看当前的形势，雷米思想要叛变
Look at the situation, Ramius intends to defect.
俄国人知道这点，因此他们想击沉他
The Russians know this, which is why they've tried to sink him,
但是他们不能…
but they haven't been able to...
- 我想出一套攻击方案  - 很好
- I have a firing solution. - Very well.
舰长，你必须要听我说
Captain, you have to listen to me.
俄国人不能阻止雷米思叛变
The Russians will stop at nothing to prevent Ramius from defecting.
他们编造故事说他疯了
They've invented this story that he's crazy
是因为他们需要我们的帮助消灭他
because they need us to sink him before he can contact us.
检查武器，要保证绝对安全
Weapons Control, I want full safeties.
我不想放掉这条大鱼
I don't want this fish coming back.
是的，长官
Full safety.
舰长，我了解他
Captain, I know this man.
他有没有再做出大回转？
Has he made any Crazy Ivans?
那有什么不同吗？
What difference does that make?
- 他下一步会向右转  - 因为他上次是向左转？
- The next one will be to starboard. - Why? Because his last was to port?
因为他习惯后半段右转
Because he goes to starboard in the bottom half of the hour.
一号二号鱼雷管准备发射
Flood tubes one and two. Warm up the weapons.
肯定有办法在不违反规定的情况下和他取得联系
Find a way to establish contact without violating orders.
我跟你说，他要叛变
He wants to defect!
汤普森先生
Mr. Thompson,
让华生长官带武器到指挥舱来
call Chief Watson to the conn with his sidearm.
指挥舱，这里是声纳室，信噪比在下降
Conn, Sonar. Signal to noise ratio's dropping.
目标可能改变了方向
Possible aspect change in target.
目标正在转向
Possible target zig based on bearing rate.
指挥舱，这里是声纳 大回转
Conn, Sonar. Crazy Ivan!
舰长
Captain.
舰长，他转向了
Captain, he's turning.
- 向哪个方向？  - 向右，长官
- Which way is he turning? - To the starboard, sir.
给他一次机会吧
Give the man a chance.
全速后退
All back full.
- 舰长，再说一遍  - 我说全速后退
- Captain, say again. - I said all back full!
- 全速后退  - 引擎全速后退
Back full. Aye, sir. Engines back full.
他们能听到我们
We're cavitating. He can hear us!
静止不动
Conn, aye.
静止
All stop.
是
All stop, aye.
我们暴露了行踪
All right. We just unzipped our fly.
汤普森先生
Mr. Thompson,
把外舱门打开
open the outer doors.
取消程序
Firing point procedures.
如果那混蛋耍什么花招
Now, if that bastard so much as twitches,
我就把他打到火星上去
I'm going to blow him right to Mars.
船腹部舵手停止运行
All stop rudder amidships.
什么情况？
What's going on?
你能辨别来者吗？
Can you identify the contact?
是一艘洛杉矶级美国攻击潜艇，方位015…
American Los Angeles class attack submarine bearing 0-1-5...
船长，有尖锐的金属撞击声
Captain, sharp metallic transients.
他可能要开启鱼雷管
He may be trying to open his torpedo tube doors.
一号二号弹道的外舱门已经打开
Outer doors are open on tubes one and two.
- 准备发射  - 很好
- We're ready to shoot. - Very well.
我收到的命令很清楚，莱恩先生
My orders are specific, Mr. Ryan.
他已经打开了外舱门，正准备射击
He's opened his outer doors. He's preparing to fire.
三号四号鱼雷准备就绪，准备应战
Flood tubes three and four and plot a solution.
明白船长三四号弹道准备，准备应战
Captain, flood tubes three and four. Plot solution.
打开鱼雷管的门吗，长官？
Shall I open the torpedo tube door, sir?
舰长，打开外舱门吗？
Captain, shall I open outer doors?
不
No.
将发射指令改由电脑控制
Lock the firing solution into the computer.
不要打开外舱门
Do not open the doors.
是，船长
Aye, Captain.
将发射指令改由电脑控制
Lock solution into computer.
指挥舱，这是声纳，目标在发射管内装好了炮弹
Conn, Sonar. Target's flooded his tubes.
他打开外舱门了吗？
Has he opened his outer doors?
没有船长，它只是停在那里
Negative, Captain. He's just sitting there.
等一下
Hold on.
船体突然行动，往浅水区去了
Hull popping. Target's coming shallow.
什么意思？
What's that mean?
那意味着你的俄国朋友很聪明
That means he's a very cool customer, your Russian.
他知道我们在这里
He knows we're here and ready to shoot.
他并没有要挑衅我们
He's not provoking us.
他要上升到了望深度，看水面上的情况
He's heading to periscope depth to see what's on the surface.
- 他现在的航线是什么？  - 是270航线
- What's his course? - His course is 2-7-0,
向西
due west.
- 我们跟上他  - 是，船长
- Bring us alongside him. - Aye, aye, Captain.
声纳，这是指挥舱，报告一下所有的联系信号
Sonar, Conn. Report all contacts.
指挥舱，声纳
Conn, Sonar.
唯一联系信号就是台风七号，方位195
My only contact is Typhoon 7, bearing 1-9-5.
很好
Very well.
控制中心，目标的射程多少？
Fire control, range to target?
射程是300码
Range is 300 yards.
把你的深度调整到65英尺
Make your depth 65 feet.
潜水官，把你的深度调整到65英尺
Diving Officer, make your depth 65 feet.
他想要到上面去窥视一下
He wants to go up and take a peek.
我们陪他玩玩
We'll play along.
- 深度将要到达45米  - 深度将要到达45米
- Going to 45. - Going to 45.
- 武器的情况？  - 准备就绪
- Weapons status? - Weapons are on.
三、四号鱼雷管已装好弹药，外舱门闭合
Tubes three and four are flooded. Outer doors are closed.
- 25米  - 深度25米
- Twenty-five meters. - Depth 25 meters.
标记上这个方位
Mark this bearing.
莱恩先生，你不是想跟他说话？
You wanted to talk to him, Mr. Ryan.
他就在那
There he is.
你想要说什么？
What do you want to say?
只有他单独使用潜望镜吗？
Is he the only one looking?
可能吧
Probably.
我们必须要抓住这次机会
We'll have to chance that.
“美国被通知你将发射飞弹”
"U.S. told you intend missile launch." Break.
“不要接近美国海岸，否则你将要遭到攻击”
"Do not approach U.S. coast or you will be attacked."
完毕
Break.
“如果有其他意图…”
"If intention is other...
“请诚实告知”
will you discuss option?"
完毕
Break.
他看得懂密码吗？
Can he acknowledge with a single ping?
问题是他想不想？
Yeah, he can. The question is, will he?
回应对方
Verify our range to target.
只打一下闪光
One ping only.
是，船长
Aye, Captain.
我会受到谴责的
I'll be damned.
现在要说什么？
Now what?
好吧
All right.
“如果要投诚…”
"If defection...
“你就把航线朝向…”
"you plot course toward..."
图表
The chart.
我需要一份图表
I need a chart.
不是这个
No. No.
我们现在到底在哪？
Okay. Where the hell are we?
下面某地，下面某地
Someplace deep. Someplace deep.
（劳伦系深水区）
把这个发给他！
Send them this!
就发吧
Just send it.
你疯了吗？
You out of your mind?
就发吧
Just send it.
告诉我一件事
Tell me one thing.
你是怎么知道他那时要向右转？
How did you know he was going to go to starboard?
我不知道
I didn't.
我有一半的机会说服你，我必须冒险
I had a 50/50 chance. I needed a break.
对不起
Sorry.
那好吧，莱恩先生
That's all right, Mr. Ryan.
我对摩斯码不太熟悉
My Morse is so rusty
我可能会耗费一个月的时间来向我们的玩伴发送消息
I may be sending dimensions on playmate of the month.
核实我们与目标的距离
Reverify our range to target.
回应他一次闪光
One ping only.
舰长，我…
Captain, I just...
发出一个信号，瓦西里
Give me a ping, Vasily.
请发送一个信号
One ping only, please.
是，舰长
Aye, Captain.
这是什么意思？
What the hell is this about?
俄国人想让我们击沉它
The Russians want us to sink her.
我们可能必须要那样做
We might have to do that.
我们必须给美国人腾些地方
We must give this American a wide berth.
我们向南走
Let us turn south.
卡玛若夫先生…
Mr. Kamarov.
绘出一条向南的新航线
Plot a new course due south.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
新航线180
New course 1-8-0.
（大浅滩  位于劳伦系深水区北部）
（20小时后）
是反应炉，关闭反应炉
It's the reactor! Shut down the reactor!
关闭通风系统
Seal the ventilation system!
通风系统的控制器坏了！
The ventilation controls have failed!
大家快从舱房出来
Everybody out. Clear the compartment!
出来！
Out!
通风系统马上关闭
Ventilation system, shut it down now.
他们没有回应，控制器没有反应
They don't respond. The controls don't respond!
手动关闭它，快点！关上它
Bypass it. Seal it manually! Move! Shut it off.
麦勒金，再说一遍
Melekhin, say again.
由于冷却系统发生泄漏
Suffered a leak in the primary coolant tube,
反应炉已经关闭
so shut down the reactor,
但是通风系统坏了
but the ventilation circuits have been disabled.
冷却系统好像被严重污染了
The coolant appears highly contaminated.
我就知道履带推进器出问题了
I knew there was damage when the caterpillar went down.
正在向各个舱房发出辐射警报
Radiation alarms activating in all compartments.
引擎受到了严重的污染
Engineering is heavily contaminated,
辐射正在袭来
and radiation's moving forward.
去到潜望深度，与外面的空气流通一下
Get to periscope depth. Ventilate with outside air.
是，船长，到达潜望深度
Aye, Captain. Periscope depth!
- 准备通风  - 通风不会有什么作用
- Prepare to ventilate! - Ventilating won't do anything.
我们必须疏散他们
We've got to get them off.
电池的电量还有多少？
What's the battery condition?
四小时，省一点可以用六小时
Four hours. Six, if we're cautious.
启用电池系统
Engage battery system.
我们遭到了一级辐射泄漏
We've got a level one radiation leak.
潜艇的各个角落都被污染了
Every surface of this ship's contaminated.
只是通风不会起到任何作用，我们必须离开潜艇
We've got to get the men off.
长官，我们被人蓄意破坏了
Sir, we have been sabotaged!
谁说的？
Who said anything about sabotage?
舰长
Captain!
长官，医生是对的
Sir, I'm afraid the doctor is right.
很好
Very well.
到水面上去，我们要把人员疏散到甲板上
Surface. We'll evacuate the men to the deck.
是，船长，使潜艇浮出水面
Aye, Captain. Surface the ship!
召集所有人员到逃生舱口
Prepare to muster all personnel to escape hatches.
拿出所有的救生艇，把它们放到甲板上
Break out the rafts. Lash them to the deck.
在舰队到来之前，救生艇将会是我们的避难所
We'll use them as shelters until the fleet arrives.
务必确定所有船员确实疏散
Make sure the count is accurate, Doctor.
我们必须让所有人都逃出去
We must get the entire crew out.
是，长官
Yes, sir.
卫兵士官报告说救生艇很安全，正在进行疏散
Master-at-arms reports rafts secure and evacuation proceeding.
很好
Very good.
我们轮流去指挥舱
We'll rotate through the conn.
不要让任何人停留超过20分钟的时间
No officer will spend more than 20 minutes below deck.
- 那样行吗？  - 可以，舰长
- Will that be satisfactory? - Completely, Captain.
水面信号
Surface contact,
方位270
2-7-0,
距离六英哩并迅速接近中
six miles and closing fast.
是一艘军舰
It's a warship.
什么？你确定吗？
What? Here? Can you identify it?
是一艘护卫舰
It's a frigate,
可能是美国的
U.S., probably,
佩里级，他正在发出信号
Perry class. He's signaling.
“红色十月号，红色十月号”
"Red October. Red October.
“别动，待在原地”
Halt and stay where you are.
“勿试图潜入水中，以免遭到攻击”
"Do not attempt to submerge, or you will be fired upon."
舰长，我觉得他是想让我们登船
Captain, I think he means to board us.
你和船员们去
You will go with the crew.
我和指挥官们将会潜入你们下方
The officers and I will submerge beneath you
追赶这艘舰艇
and scuttle the ship.
你会因此得到列宁勋章的，舰长
You'll receive the Order of Lenin for this, Captain.
我们离开
We're going to cast off.
舰长要击沉这艘舰艇
The captain's going to scuttle the ship.
他正在下潜，长官
He's going down, sir.
向他的船头方向射击，向右到达180航线
Put a shot across his bow. Come right at 1-8-0.
海鹰一号，起飞
Seahawk One, this is bravo command.
她准备好了
She's ready.
海鹰一号，立刻发射鱼雷
Seahawk One, release on my command.
投射、投射
Drop now, now, now.
与目标的距离900码
Range to target, 900 yards.
800码
Eight hundred yards.
700码
Seven hundred yards.
600码
Six hundred yards.
500码
Five hundred yards.
400码
Four hundred yards.
300码
Three hundred yards.
鱼雷被引爆了
The torpedo is detonated.
现在
Now,
我明白，指挥官
understand, Commander,
鱼雷不是自己引爆的
that torpedo did not self-destruct.
你听到它击中了船体
You heard it hit the hull.
而我从来没有出现在这里
And I was never here.
联系达拉斯号，让他们出发
Contact Dallas. Give them the go.
通知达拉斯号，让深潜救助艇行动
Advise Dallas. Get the DSRV moving.
达拉斯号，我是鲁本吉姆斯
Dallas, this is Rueben James.
这么惊险的行动
There are about two million things
随时都可能出问题
that can still go wrong with this stunt.
中央情报局
Central Intelligence Agency.
这里明显是有矛盾
Now, there's a contradiction in terms.
来杯咖啡怎么样，莱恩？
How's the coffee, Ryan?
达拉斯号，这里是神秘号，请求起航
Dallas, this is the Mystic. Request clearance for launch.
神秘号，这里是达拉斯号，准许你起航
Mystic, Dallas. You're cleared for launch.
舱门安全
Hatch is secured.
生命维持器正常，起航前检查完毕
Life support, normal. Prelaunch checks complete.
- 我们准备起航  - 是
- We're ready to launch. - Aye.
- 准备入水  - 准备入水
- Flood the skirt. - Flood the skirt. Aye.
注水完成并保持平衡
Skirt's filled and equalized.
软密封，准备出发
Soft seal. Ready to lift off.
来吧
Okay. Let's do it.
我们出发了
We're off.
拥有强大推动力的港口
Thrusting port.
距离600码并持续接近
Six hundred yards and closing.
沿着075航线行驶
Steer right to course 0-7-5.
400码
Four hundred.
200码
Two hundred yards.
100码
One hundred yards.
把灯打开
Hit the lights.
天啊，是个大家伙
Jesus, that's a big sucker.
好了，我们已经到位了
Okay, we're in position.
你可以打开舱门了
You can open the hatch.
等一下，琼斯
Hold it a second. Jonesy.
莱恩先生
Mr. Ryan.
他是要叛变
He's defecting.
他不会改主意吗？
And he can't change his mind?
他不会改变主意的
He's not going to change his mind.
你要把命赌在那上面吗？
You willing to bet your life on that?
- 长官，能把锤子递给我吗？  - 好
- Sir, could you hand me that hammer? - Yeah.
美国人
Americans.
他的脸都吓绿了
He's turning green.
你笑什么？
What's so funny?
我们舰长以为你是像牛仔一样的人
The captain seems to think you're some sort of cowboy.
你会说俄语
You speak Russian.
会一点
A little.
学习敌人的说话方式是很明智的行为
It's wise to study the ways of one's adversary.
你不这样认为吗？
Don't you think?
确实是
It is.
我怀疑你是否还记得
I doubt you'd remember,
我们曾在列宁格勒的领事馆见过一面
but we met once at the Consulate in Leningrad.
还有你的妻子，非常抱歉
Along with your wife. I'm very sorry.
你凭什么向我的潜艇开炮？
What gives you the right to fire on my ship?
你们的信息并没有提到鱼雷
Your signal said nothing of a torpedo.
莱恩
Ryan.
有必要给你的船员制造一个假象
It was necessary to maintain the illusion for your crew.
我的船员们得到救援了吗？
My crew are being rescued, yes?
像我们说的那样
As we speak.
- 是你发送的信息  - 对，长官
- You sent the signal. - That's correct, sir.
你是怎么知道我们的反应炉事故是假象？
Then how did you know our reactor accident was false?
猜的，但符合逻辑
That was a guess, but it seemed logical.
很好
Very well.
我们送给你们…
I present you...
红色十月号弹道导弹潜艇
the ballistic missile submarine Red October.
我和指挥官们要求庇护…
My officers and I request asylum...
在美国境内寻求
in the United States of America.
很荣幸，先生
It's a pleasure, sir.
巴特・曼库索，美国达拉斯号军舰
Bart Mancuso, USS Dallas.
鱼雷，美国人又在向我们射击
Torpedo. The Americans are shooting at us again.
射程太高了
The pitch is too high.
鱼雷是俄国人射的
The torpedo's Russian.
你说另一枚水雷是什么意思？它打哪来？
What do you mean another torpedo? Where the hell did it come from?
指挥舱，这里是声纳，新的信号，塞拉41号
Conn, Sonar. New contact. Sierra 4-1.
阿法级苏联潜艇
Alfa class Soviet submarine.
为什么我听不到爆炸声？
Why don't I have a detonation?
武器只能对着目标的远端发射
The weapon enabled on the far side of the target.
而它在射击前已经超过了红色十月号
It passed Red October before arming.
我们搞错了射程，按照正确的设定再次开火
We got wrong range, fire again with the right settings
两个发射管重新装上炮弹
and reload both tubes.
武力准备
Get me power.
- 让那鬼东西离我的潜艇远点  - 它会的
- Get that damn thing off my boat. - It's off.
又有人向我们发射了鱼雷
I think somebody shot a torpedo at us.
- 赶快离开这里  - 哪里…
- No shit, buckwheat. Get out of here. - Where am I...
舰长正在教训他们
The Captain is fighting them.
舰长正在和美国人战斗
The Captain is fighting the Americans.
伯罗丁，射击控制
Borodin, fire control.
莱恩，坐到这来
Ryan. Sit here.
我不是海军指挥官 我是中央情报局的
I'm not a naval officer. I'm with the CIA.
- 中央情报局？  - 我不是特工
- CIA? - I'm not an agent.
我只是为中央情报局写书
I just write books for the CIA.
管他的，坐下，按照我说的做
Whatever. Sit down. And do exactly what I tell you.
深潜救助艇离开了
DSRVs away.
右舷八千码处有一艘阿法级苏联潜艇
There's a Russian Alfa 8,000 yards to starboard.
我认为那是科洛瓦罗夫
I think it's the Konovalov.
- 侧翼加速  - 侧翼加速
- Increase the flank. - Increase the flank.
怎么做？
How?
按钮转到右满舵
That knob. Turn right full.
全速前进，右满舵
All ahead flank. Right full rudder.
- 长官，他又在射击了  - 准备应战
- He's shooting again, sir. - Go to battle stations.
准备应战
Battle stations.
指挥官，开启武器系统
Chief of Watch, man battle stations.
水中发现鱼雷，方位315
Torpedo in the water. Bearing 3-1-5.
距离七千码
Make range 7,000 yards.
向右转舵到315
Steer right 3-1-5.
那是朝着鱼雷方向
That's heading into the torpedo.
按原定方向走315
Steady, bearing still 3-1-5.
估算距离为六千码
Estimated range, 6,000 yards.
还是在315方向
Still 3-1-5.
右转舵，直到这里显示315
Steer right till this reads 3-1-5.
那样不对
No, that's wrong.
莱恩，千万不要转动方向盘
Ryan, don't turn that god damn wheel.
方位315
3-1-5.
你这是直接冲着水雷去的
You're heading straight into that torpedo.
- 是的  - 他在做什么？
- Yes. - Doing what?
- 他转向正对鱼雷  - 什么？
- He's turned into the torpedo's path. - What?
长官，红色十月号正对鱼雷
Red October's turned directly into the torpedo's path, sir.
我的天
Mother of God.
鱼雷还在315方向，距离五千码
Torpedo steady, bearing 3-1-5. Range, 5,000 yards.
麦勒金，再快点
Melekhin, more speed.
不行，航速已达110
Negative. We are already running 110%.
那就以115的速度
Then get me 115%.
距离大概有三千码
Estimate range 3,000 yards.
并且在以惊人的速度接近
Closing awfully fast.
他朝着鱼雷去了，他想干什么，自杀吗？
He's heading right into the torpedo. What's he trying to do, kill himself?
汤普森，我们有反击能力
We have a firing solution on the Russian Alfa.
- 我们可以回击吗？  - 他们又没向我们开炮
- Can we shoot back? - They didn't shoot at us.
未经授权，我不能袭击苏联潜艇
I can't attack a Soviet submarine without authorization.
鱼雷方向还是315
Torpedo bearing, steady at 3-1-5.
距离最多只有九百码
Best range, 900 yards.
水雷将在二十秒后击中我们
Torpedo impact, 20 seconds.
什么书？
What books?
你说什么？
Pardon me?
你写的是什么书？
What books did you write?
我为哈尔西将军写了本自传
I wrote a biography on Admiral Halsey
名字叫做《战斗水手》
called The Fighting Sailor,
是关于海战战术的
about naval combat tactics.
我知道这本书
I know this book.
水雷撞击…
Torpedo impact...
你的结论是错，莱恩
Your conclusions were all wrong, Ryan.
十秒
Ten seconds.
哈尔西的做法很愚蠢
Halsey acted stupidly.
九、八、七、六
Nine, eight, seven, six,
五、四、三、二…
five, four, three, two...
鱼雷撞击…
Torpedo impact...
现在
Now.
真该死
I'll be damned.
怎么了？
What happened?
这是战术，莱恩先生
Combat tactics, Mr. Ryan.
舰长朝着鱼雷前进
By turning into the torpedo,
鱼雷因距离太近，无法及时引爆
the captain closed the distance before it could arm itself.
- 就这样吗？  - 不完全是
- So that's it? - Not quite.
托普洛夫船长
Right now, Captain Tupolev
正在消除所有武器的安全设置
is removing the safety features on all his weapons.
他不会再犯同样的错误
He won't make the same mistake twice.
瓦西里，想出对策了吗？
Vasily, have you plotted a solution yet?
是，船长，可能有些粗糙，但…
Aye, Captain. It's a little rough, but I...
枪声？
Gunfire?
好像是的，长官
That's what it sounded like, sir.
不会改变他的想法？
Won't change his mind?
是一名船员
It's one of the crew.
不管他是谁，都会重新考虑的
Whoever he is, he's having second thoughts.
我本来可以去蒙大拿州的
I would like to have seen Montana.
舰长，他朝导弹舱去了
Captain, he stumbled forward into the missile bay.
左舷二十号弹筒舱发出警报
There's a silo hatch warning port side, number 20.
他想要发射导弹
He can't launch a missile.
不是，但他可以搞破坏
No, but he can blow one up.
- 舰长，接管指挥舱  - 射击控制舱会被炸飞
- Captain, take the conn. - Fire control's blasted to hell.
到他后面去停在那
Then get behind him and stay there.
舰长，等一下
Captain, wait.
你可能需要这个，长官
You may need this, sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
不要只是站在那里，莱恩，跟他去
Don't just stand there, Ryan. Go with him!
- 你会说英语吗？  - 会，先生
- You, you speak English? - Yes, sir.
你过来
Get your butt over here.
舰长，鱼雷在撞击时中断了信号
Captain, torpedo broke off on impact.
把安全范围设置到零
Set the safety ranges for zero.
已经到极限了
I cannot go any faster.
我们必须在他到达点火装置前抓住他
We must get him before he gets to the ignition circuits.
如果他到达点火装置会怎样？
What happens if he gets to that ignition circuitry?
他会毁掉这艘潜艇
He can incinerate the ship.
那扇门是从这出去唯一的道路吗？
Is that door the only way out of here?
是的
Yes.
不要让他从这跑了
Don't let him get past you.
莱恩
Ryan.
不要随便开枪
Be careful what you shoot at.
这里的大部分东西…
Most things in here...
是经不起子弹射击的
don't react too well to bullets.
好
Right.
我不能随便开枪？
I have to be careful what I shoot at?
安全范围设置为零了
Safety ranges set to zero.
告诉我红色十月号的方位
Sonar, give me the bearing for Red October.
它在我们后面
She's positioned behind us.
右满舵，我要彻底打败他
Right full rudder! I'll shake the man loose.
- 它向下潜了  - 向下三十度
- He's going deep. - Thirty degree down angle!
这是所有的反制策略吗？
All the countermeasures were over there, right?
很好
Very well.
将军，阿法级潜艇速度太快
Admiral, the Alfa's too quick.
红色十月迟早会被歼灭
It's only a matter of time.
莱恩
"Ryan,
这里的某些东西禁不起子弹射击
some things in here don't react well to bullets."
是啊
Yeah.
就像我
Like me.
我禁不起子弹射击
I don't react well to bullets.
- 现在位置，琼斯？  - 很近，长官
- Where's he now? - Close, sir.
正前方900米
Nine hundred meters, directly ahead.
抓住他了
Got him.
- 锁定它，准备发射鱼雷  - 我们离得太近了
- Match bearings and fire. - We are too close!
别吵，发动武器
Don't argue. Launch the weapon.
鱼雷已全部装填，最好不要…
The torpedoes are armed in the tubes! You cannot...
现在发射
Do it now!
另一枚水雷 已进入引爆程序
Another torpedo. It went active the moment it was launched.
它朝我们来了
左满舵 全速左转，船头微倾
Left full rudder. Ease off on your bow planes.
我认为他找到我们了
I think he's got us.
做得好！达拉斯号
Way to go, Dallas!
捕捉到了鱼雷的信息，距离五百码并持续接近
Torpedo is in acquisition. Range 500 yards and closing.
汤普森先生，你做到了！
You've done it, Mr. Thompson!
感谢上帝
I hope this works.
指挥官，升到水面上去
Chief, put us on the roof.
反导控制中心，听我的指令
Countermeasure station, on my mark.
五、四…
Five, four...
发射反导导弹，紧急发射
One. Release countermeasures. Emergency blow!
全速上升，紧急排气
Full rise. Fair water plane.
600英尺，550英尺
Six hundred feet, 550,
500英尺
500 feet.
- 450英尺  - 来吧，达拉斯
- Four-fifty. - Come on, big D. Fly.
舰长把他们吓得浮出了水面
Captain scared 'em out of the water!
鱼雷仍处在活跃状态
That torpedo's still active.
正在寻找另一个目标
It's searching for another target.
一个该死的厨师！
A goddamn cook!
它锁定我们了！
阿法级潜艇离我们多近，琼斯？
How close is that Alfa, Jonesy?
船尾方向1000码向左舷方向行进
Thousand yards, going to port.
改变方向
Reverse your turn.
我们正转向他
We're turning straight at him.
鱼雷还在我们后面
Torpedo's still on our tail.
玩老鹰抓小鸡最难的就是知道何时应该退缩
The hard part about playing chicken is knowing when to flinch.
还有400码
Collision in 400 yards,
350码、300码…
350, 300...
舰长
Captain!
右满舵，向下潜30度
Right full rudder, 30 degree down angle.
是，长官，太近了
Aye, sir. This one's going to be close.
正前方有鱼雷
Torpedo dead ahead!
你这个自大狂害死了我们
You arrogant ass. You've killed us.
我们已经调查过红色十月号最后出没的地点了
We have ascertained the Red October's final position,
但是海水太深了
but given the depth of the water
而且残骸散落在那样广阔的水域中
and the fact that the wreckage spreads across a wide area,
我们还需要花些时间来调查清楚
it'll be some time before anything's recovered.
贵国正在向船员求证
However, your people are interviewing the crew now
并正在安排他们的回程
and making arrangements for their return.
这件事情真是太不幸了，大使先生
This has been a terrible tragedy, Mr. Ambassador.
而且我想强调，如果你早点来找我们
And I can only stress that if you'd come to us earlier
事情也许可以避免
it might have been avoided.
我很感谢你能公正的处理这件事
I appreciate your candor in the matter.
我也是，安德烈
And I yours, Andrei.
也许不久以后，科技能发展的更先进
Perhaps in the future, the technology will be available,
使我们能对残骸进行彻底的调查
allow a more thorough investigation of the wreckage.
也许吧
Perhaps.
还有一件事…
There is another matter...
很难以启齿…
One that I'm reluctant to...
请讲
Please.
我们的一艘阿法级潜艇
One of our submarines, an Alfa,
最近的一次报告显示她在大浅滩区域
was last reported in the area of the Grand Banks.
我们有段时间没有它的消息
We have not heard from her for some time.
安德烈
Andrei.
你又丢失了另一艘潜艇
You've lost another submarine?
（佩诺布斯科特河  海港北部，缅因州）
一路上
All this way...
我们都把潜艇藏一条河里
to hide a submarine in a river.
我们距离最近的海军基地只有100英哩
We're 100 miles from the nearest naval base,
那里卫星是观测不到的
the last place that satellites will ever look.
我就在这里长大
I grew up around here.
我的祖父就在那座小岛附近教我钓鱼
My grandfather taught me to fish off that island right over there.
你还有一个问题没有问我
There's one question you haven't asked me yet.
“为什么那样做？”
Why?
我觉得你准备好了就会给我答案的
I figured you would tell me when you were ready.
有一部分人认为
Now, there are those who believe
我们应该首先攻击美国
we should attack the United States first,
瞬间解决一切问题
settle everything in one moment.
红色十月号就是为这个目的而建造的
Red October was built for that purpose.
这样做了之后
When the dust settles from this,
莫斯科又会烽火连天
there's going to be hell to pay in Moscow.
也许吧
Perhaps.
或许这样反而好
Maybe something good will come from it.
有时来个小变革
A little revolution, now and then,
是件好事，你不这样认为吗？
is a healthy thing, don't you think?
莱恩，你还喜欢钓鱼吗？
Do you still like to fish, Ryan?
有一条河，跟这条河差不多
There's a river, not unlike this one,
在维尔纽斯附近
near Vilnius,
我的祖父曾在那里教我钓鱼
where my grandfather taught me to fish.
“大海为每个人带来新的希望”
"And the sea will grant each man new hope
“就像是睡眠带来家中的梦境”
"as sleep brings dreams of home."
克里斯多弗・哥伦布（意大利航海家）
Christopher Columbus.
欢迎来到新世界，长官
Welcome to the New World, sir.
先生，一切都还好吧？
Everything all right, sir?
双语制作：dahongying